<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>A believers triumph over death exemplified in a relation of the last hours of Dr. Andrew Rivet and an account of divers other remarkable instances : being an history of the comfortable end and dying words of several eminent men, with other occasional passages, all tending to comfort Christians against the fear of death and prepare them for a like happy change.</title>
            <author>Coxe, Nehemiah.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1682</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 191 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 125 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2014-11">2014-11 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">B20782</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing C6716</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">09673967</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 09673967</idno>
            <idno type="VID">204449</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online text creation partnership.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. B20782)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 204449)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 1328:22)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>A believers triumph over death exemplified in a relation of the last hours of Dr. Andrew Rivet and an account of divers other remarkable instances : being an history of the comfortable end and dying words of several eminent men, with other occasional passages, all tending to comfort Christians against the fear of death and prepare them for a like happy change.</title>
                  <author>Coxe, Nehemiah.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[10], 232 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed for Benjamin Alsop,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1682.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>"Preface" signed: Nehemiah Coxe.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in the Harvard University Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Rivet, André, 1572-1651.</term>
               <term>Death.</term>
               <term>Translation to heaven.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2013-07</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-07</date>
            <label>Apex CoVantage</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-09</date>
            <label>Leigh Rupinski</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-09</date>
            <label>Leigh Rupinski</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-03</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:204449:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:204449:1"/>
            <p> A Believers Triumph OVER DEATH, Exemplified in a RELATION OF The LAST HOURS OF D<hi rend="sup">r</hi> 
               <hi>ANDREW RIVET.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>AND An Account of divers other Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>markable Inſtances.</p>
            <p>BEING An Hiſtory of the <hi>Comfortable End,</hi> and <hi>dying Words</hi> of ſeveral eminent Men; with other Occaſional Paſſages: All tending to comfort Chriſtians againſt the Fear of Death, and prepare them for a like Happy Change.</p>
            <q>
               <hi>He ſhall enter into Peace: They ſhall reſt in their Beds, each one walking in his <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>prightneſs.</hi>
               <bibl>Iſa. 57. 2.</bibl>
            </q>
            <p>
               <hi>London,</hi> Printed for <hi>Benjamin Alſop</hi> at the <hi>Angel</hi> and <hi>Bible</hi> in the <hi>Poultrey,</hi> 1682.</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:204449:2" rendition="simple:additions"/>
         </div>
         <div type="preface">
            <pb facs="tcp:204449:2"/>
            <head>The PREFACE.</head>
            <p>
               <hi>I</hi> Will not trouble the Reader with a long Preface to a little Book, nor waſte Time in an affected Apology for my Undertaking to publiſh the en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſuing Stories in the Engliſh Tongue; for I doubt not but up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on a ſerious Peruſal, the things here Related will be eſteemed by every Pious Chriſtian of that worth and uſe, as will ſuffici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ently recommend this Account of them to their good acceptance, who were not capable of reading them in another Language.</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:204449:3"/>
            <p> The firſt, and largeſt part, of what is here offered to your Service, (viz. <hi>The laſt Hours of Dr.</hi> Rivet) was firſt written, and publiſhed in the French Tongue, and ſoon after turned into Latine, and printed again in the laſt Edition of his learned and elaborate Works; from whence you have it now tranſlated into our own Language: I have added nothing of my own to it, nor omit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted the mention of the leaſt cir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cumſtance there ſet down, but have faithfully repreſented the whole in the ſame order as I met with it my ſelf: And I may modeſtly ſay, 'Tis as great <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> Story of this kind as moſt Age<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> can furniſh us with. That thi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb facs="tcp:204449:3"/> might not go alone, I have in the <hi>Appendix</hi> added the Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>morable Examples of the Bleſſed and Peaceful End of ſome others alſo, eminent for their Piety, and zealous Profeſſion of the Proteſtant Religion while they lived: In which (where no other Author is cited) I have followed the Authority of <hi>Melchior Ada<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mus,</hi> or of thoſe from whom he made his Collections; and do aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure you, that as there is nothing Reported without good Warrant, as to the truth of matter of fact, ſo I am confident nothing will occurre, but what is ſuitable to feed and increaſe thoſe holy Af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fections, and that Pious Zeal, which I hope the foregoing Nar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rative
<pb facs="tcp:204449:4"/> may enkindle in the Rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders heart.</p>
            <p>That which I aim at in the whole is, the Quickening and Encouragement of Chriſtians in their ſpiritual Courſe; and that the weighty Sayings, and happy End of theſe Great men may provoke us to imitate that wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thy Pattern of Faith and Holi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, which they have left us both living and dying: Inſtructi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on backt by Example is more powerful than that given by Precept alone: 'Tis truly ſaid, <hi>Verba docent; Exempla tra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hunt:</hi> i. e. <hi>Words teach,</hi> but <hi>Examples draw:</hi> Howbeit, even the Words of <hi>Dying men</hi> do uſually make a deeper Im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſion
<pb facs="tcp:204449:4"/> upon the Heart, than other Diſcourſes can doe: The Sayings of one upon the brink of Eternity are next of kin to thoſe of one returned from the Dead, and ſent back from another World to give us Warning, and direction in our way thither, and therefore do juſtly claim a more than ordinary attention from us. Theſe men call to us from the borders of Light, having alrea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy taſted the Fruit of the hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venly <hi>Canaan;</hi> and have left behind them ſuch a feeling Te<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtimony of its Sweetneſs and Glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry, as may greatly engage our Souls in purſuit after that ſame Bleſſedneſs which they are arri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved at. And if we would have
<pb facs="tcp:204449:5"/> our Death to be as Gainf<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> and Comfortable as theirs, w<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> muſt make the Glory of Chriſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> the higheſt End and Deſign o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> our Lives, as they did. Wha<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> is the Talent of Time lent u<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> for, but that we might wor<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> out our own Salvation with fea<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> and trembling? We loſe all ou<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> time and pains that are not em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ployed this way; and ſhall a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> laſt be of his mind that ſaid upon his Death-bed, <hi>I repent</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Dr. <hi>Donn.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>of all my Life, but that part of it which I ſpent in Communion with God and doing Good.</hi> All the World will not relieve a Dying Man; <hi>For what will it profit a</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Matt. 16. 26.</note> 
               <hi>man if he Gain the whole</hi>
               <pb facs="tcp:204449:5"/> 
               <hi>World, and loſe his own Soul? or what ſhall a man give in Exchange for his Soul?</hi> The greateſt Monarch that dyes without Grace, muſt ſubſcribe to the laſt words of <hi>Sept. Severus</hi> the Roman Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perour, <note place="margin">Pezel. Mellif.</note> 
               <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>. i. e. <hi>I have been all things, and nothing profits me.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>I cannot but adde the Grave and ſerious words of <hi>Salma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſius,</hi> who was a Man of Great Learning, of extraordinary dili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gence in his Studies, and of Great Fame among the Scholars of this laſt Age; and yet upon his Death-bed he pours forth this bitter Complaint:</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:204449:6"/>
            <p>
               <q>Oh I have loſt a deal of Time! Time! that moſt pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cious thing in the World, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of had I but one Year longer, it ſhould be ſpent in Reading <hi>David</hi>'s Pſalms, and <hi>Paul</hi>'s Epiſtles: Oh Sirs, mind the World leſs, and God more; All the Learning in the World without Piety, and the true Fear of God, is nothing worth: The Fear of the Lord that is Wiſdom, and to Depart from Evil that is Underſtanding.</q>
            </p>
            <p>In like manner, the Great <hi>Hugo Grotius,</hi> after all his Labour, Study, and Proficiency in other Knowledge, at the cloſe of his Life told his Friends, <q>That he would give all his
<pb facs="tcp:204449:6"/> Learning and Honour for the Plain Integrity and Piety of <hi>John Urick;</hi> who was a de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vout Poor man, that ſpent eight hours of his time in Pray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er, eight in Labour, and the other eight he allowed for his Sleep and neceſſary Refreſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments.</q>
            </p>
            <p>Theſe Learned men found Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion to be the Trueſt and Beſt Wiſdom in a Dying Hour: This is the one thing needfull; and we ſhall all find it ſo, when we muſt take leave of this World, and make our appearance before God. That the following lines may thro' the Bleſſing of God be made uſeful to the awaken<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing a ſence of Religion in thoſe
<pb facs="tcp:204449:7"/> that do peruſe them, is my De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſire, and ſhall be my earneſt Prayer to him who alone can bleſs the Seed ſown, and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>creaſe the Fruits of Righteouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs.</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>Nehemiah Coxe<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
               </signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="errata">
            <head>ERRATA.</head>
            <p>THe Errors of the Preſs which diſturb th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> ſence, are thus to be corrected:</p>
            <p>Page 19. l. 23. for <hi>Order</hi> r. <hi>Ardor,</hi> p. 20. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> 10. for <hi>great very</hi> r. <hi>very great,</hi> p. 40. l. 19. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> 
               <hi>ſeeing,</hi> p. 133. l. 4. dele <hi>which,</hi> p. 200. l. 8<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> dele <hi>his.</hi>
            </p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:204449:7"/>
            <head>THE LAST HOURS OF Dr. <hi>ANDREW RIVET.</hi>
            </head>
            <div n="1-51" type="pages">
               <p>§. 1. THE multitude and variety of things memorable which do occurre in this Narrative, doth ſo much amaze us, that through fear of our own inſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficiency either to remember, or expreſs them in a due man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>er, and according to their <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ignity and worth, we cannot <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ut wiſh, this task had been <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ndertaken by abler hands. But <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>eeing it is matter of fact, and <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ords heard, which we are to
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:204449:8"/> give an account of, we had rather (ſo we may but ſerve the profit of our Friends) ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe our prudence unto cen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure, than be defective in our care and good endeavours in this matter; wherein, that we might be ſure to write no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing but moſt certain Truth, we have choſen to bury many things in oblivion, by a ſilen<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> paſſing over what we hav<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> but an imperfect remembranc<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> of; and ſhall content our ſelve<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> to make a rehearſal with ſim<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plicity and truth, of thoſe grav<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> and almoſt divine Speeches which as they were poure<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> forth by this Holy man, wer<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> faithfully preſerved, partly i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> the Memory, and partly in th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> written Notes of thoſe wh<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> conſtantly attended on him And yet though we employ ou<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> utmoſt diligence herein, w<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <pb n="3" facs="tcp:204449:8"/> ſhall never be able to give them their juſt weight and Emphaſis; for who can imitate that flowing ſtream of words which with equal wiſdom and piety proceeded from him, in an (almoſt) continued diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>courſe, for the ſpace of twelve dayes and as many nights? Or who can repreſent to the Life the motions of a mind, boyl<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing with Meditations, when the Spirit of God adminiſtred ſuch an extemporary effort of ſayings proceeding from his fruitful breaſt, and gravely uttered when his ſences were no waies impaired, as he was diverſly acted either by Grief and Fear, or Hope and Joy?</p>
               <p>§. 2. It will be but neceſſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry, before we enter upon the Relation of other things, brief<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly to mention ſomething con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerning
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:204449:9"/> the Temper and Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſition of this holy perſon, and his Circumſtances before his laſt ſickneſs, that the Grace of God towards his Servant may appear the more illuſtri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous; when we ſee with what care and Providence he diſpo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed his Affairs in the whole courſe of his life, but eſpeci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ally in this laſt act thereof.</p>
               <p>Beſides thoſe excellent gifts wherewith he was adorned (which cannot here be reckoned up particularly) through the Goodneſs of God he had been fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>voured with the enjoyment of a ſound Mind in a ſound and healthy Body; he was of a chearful and ſedate Spirit, hold<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing on in an even courſe of Life, neither lifted up with proſperity, nor caſt down by adverſity. So that by the ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bit of a comely and moderate
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:204449:9"/> deliberation, he was ever bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed with an inward Joy, and poſſeſſed all things with de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>light and Gratitude; being no leſs ready to part with them without regret and trouble, pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſuing his own profit and ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vantage in a ſerious contempla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of the vanity of all worldly things; often repeating that of the Apoſtle: <hi>The things which are ſeen are temporal, but the things which are not ſeen are eternal,</hi> 2 Cor. 4. 18. He was never moved with ſorrowful events that fell out ſuddenly, whether in publick, or in his private concerns, as a man ſurprized by an unexpected evil; neither was the tranqui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lity of his mind ſhaken by them: He was wont to ſay; <hi>Nothing is impoſſible; I wonder at no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing.</hi> Neither on the contra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry, did he at any time break forth
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:204449:10"/> into a looſe and immoderate Joy; as being one ſet in an higher place, and looking down upon all things here below as uncertain and periſhing. He never found himſelf, on any other account under ſuch per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turbation, nor ſhewed the like, as upon the deceaſe of the young Prince of <hi>Orange,</hi> who from a Child had been committed to his inſtruction and tuition; and whoſe Death (as he often af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firmed) he bewailed out of pure Charity, and not for any private loſs that himſelf might ſuſtain thereby: Becauſe the confidence he had of his excel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lent diſpoſition, and expectati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of his longer Life, had rai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed him to the hope that he would prove a uſeful Inſtru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment for the good both of the State and the Church. From that time he ſeemed to be more
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:204449:10"/> than ever drawn off from world<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly things, and uſed to ſpeak of them with a certain loath<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing and diſdain. The frame of his mind was alſo diſcove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red, by a frequent interrupting of his accuſtomed courſe of read<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the Scriptures in order in his Family, and turning to ſome ſelect Chapters, ſuch as <hi>Job</hi> 14. <hi>Eccleſ.</hi> 3. and 4. <hi>Pſal.</hi> 49. and 144. From whence he took the occaſion of ſuch diſcourſes, as ſhewed what Meditations he was cuſtomarily taken up with.</p>
               <p>§. 3. In the laſt week where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in he lived in health, being in his Garden accompanied by a Friend, and walking up and down therein, as he was wont, with great pleaſure, he gave order what he would have done in the dreſſing of ſome Trees, and then added: <hi>If I live till</hi>
                  <pb n="8" facs="tcp:204449:11"/> 
                  <hi>the Spring time, they will afford me a pleaſant ſight; but if not, I ſhall be in a Garden far more pleaſant.</hi> When his Friend in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terpoſed and ſaid, There was no cauſe why he ſhould pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſage ſuch a thing to himſelf, ſeeing he was ſound and lively; he received a Rebuke from Dr. <hi>Rivet</hi> to this purpoſe: <hi>The time is now come that I am to be treated after another manner; my age is ſo far declined and haſting to an end, as plainly to declare that death (which none can be exempted from) ſtands at my door: And truly death is the principal matter that I meditate on; God is my witneſs, that I deſire not it's delay, but am ready with a chearful mind to embrace it, yea even this day, if the will of God were ſo.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>On the ſame day he was en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>treated by Mr. <hi>Hulſius</hi> the Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtor
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:204449:11"/> of the <hi>French</hi> Church in that place <note n="*" place="margin">Breda.</note>, that on the next day, being <hi>Decemb.</hi> 25. he would preach a thankſgiving Sermon after the celebration of the Lords Supper; which he conſenting to do, choſe for his Text <hi>Pſal.</hi> 144. 3, 4. <hi>Lord, what is man that thou takeſt knowledge of him, or the Son of man that thou makeſt account of him? Man is like to Vanity; his dayes are as a ſhadow that paſſeth away.</hi> In his Sermon he had an eminent aſſiſtance from God, and deli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vered his matter with a ſtrong and clear voice, and great li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>berty of ſpeech; and chiefly applyed his diſcourſe, to ſhew what favour and honour God had vouchſafed unto man, as well in cauſing that the Son of God ſhould be a Man, as in giving him for our nouriſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment unto Eternal Life; from
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:204449:12"/> thence teaching the Notice God took of mortal men, and how it had pleaſed him to embrace them in his favour, and to mag<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nifie them.</p>
               <p>And in ſpeaking to the an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwer of the Pſalmiſt, <hi>Man is like to Vanity,</hi> he touched upon the loſs of the Prince, whoſe In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtructor he had been, which was then freſh in memory; but with words no way inclined to flattery, but becoming the Mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter and Perſon that he ſpoke of, and which breathed forth nothing but pure affection: with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>al taking notice of the Good<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs of God, who in the midſt of his Judgments had ſhewed mercy to the houſe of <hi>Orange,</hi> to which he had granted a new Offspring (a Son being then born) that the dying hope of that Noble Family might be revived before him: At length
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:204449:12"/> he cloſed with a Meditation of Death, an example of which <hi>(ſaid he)</hi> ſeeing Young men that are ſtrong, have before them in a young man ſnatch't from the earth in the flower of his age and ſtrength, it ought to be often revolved in their minds, and deep thoughts of approaching death to be enter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tained, which admits of no re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turn to life: <hi>What is man?</hi> (ſaid he) <hi>Nothing but fleſh, obnoxious to putrefaction? a flower that ſprings up to day, and to morrow is cut down: even a vapor that appeareth for a little time, and then vaniſheth away, like the breath that proceedeth out of my mouth.</hi> For the cold being great that day, did ſo condenſe his breath, that it might be ſeen of all to whom he was preach<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing.</p>
               <pb n="12" facs="tcp:204449:13"/>
               <p> §. 4. When the Sermon was fi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſhed, he returned home as lively and well as he had been ſeen for ſome years paſt; nor did he the next day feel any decay of his for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer ſtrength. But on Thurſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>day, which was the 27<hi rend="sup">th</hi> of <hi>December,</hi> he began to com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plain <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Anno</hi> 1650.</note> of a pain below his Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vel; and refuſing to eat any Supper, deſired that a Clyſter might be given him; but it was to no purpoſe, the liquor being driven back again with greater force than it was in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jected. That night was paſs'd over partly in bearing of his ſharp pains, and partly in ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rious diſcourſes. On Wedneſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>day morning the complaint of his pain was encreaſed, and he deſired that the uſe of a Clyſter might be repeated; which was done accordingly, but with no better ſucceſs than
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:204449:13"/> the former: Then were two Phyſicians ſent for, and they ſuſpecting that the former Cly<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſters either had not been skil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fully injected, or elſe were not ſtrong enough, made tryal of the like means once and again; but with the ſame ſucceſs as before: for a glutinous humour had already faſt locked up the paſſage againſt all Remedies. On the next day which was Tueſday, they preſcribed Pills of Alloes waſhed; and on Fry<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>day the Infuſion of <hi>Rhubarb;</hi> either of which did ſufficient<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly agitate his body, but effect<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed nothing, neither was any way opened for their paſſage, the expulſive faculty being weakened and dulled, ſo that it could give Nature no aſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance. The wind ſhut up in his bowels tormented the ſick man, his Belly was ſwollen,
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:204449:14"/> and he was afraid to touch either meat or drink, leſt there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by his grievance ſhould be en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>creaſed. There were no pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per means unattempted, nor any kind of help by Clyſters, Fomentations, or Baths, but were made tryal of, untill by the ſtubborn diſeaſe that reſiſted all Remedy, he was brought unto death, the twelfth day of his ſickneſs; the Hiſtory of which we ſhall now proſecute more at large.</p>
               <p>§. 5. On the ſecond day af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter his diſeaſe had ſeiſed him, he well underſtanding the na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture of it, declared what the event would be; <hi>Not</hi> (ſaith he) <hi>that I would neglect Remedies; that I may pleaſe my Friends, I will do whatſoever is thought meet to be done, being ſecure as to the iſſue, which I commit to the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vidence</hi>
                  <pb n="15" facs="tcp:204449:14"/> 
                  <hi>of God:</hi> Then he ask<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed his Neece, M<hi rend="sup">rs</hi> 
                  <hi>Mary Moline,</hi> what ſhe conceived of his diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eaſe, which he thought would prove mortal: And when ſhe anſwered, That her opinion was the ſame; <hi>yet that he had no reaſon to fear any thing, ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving been long prepared to follow God when he ſhould call; that the time of his Life hitherto had been long, if it were crowned with an happy and Glorious End.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <q>Thou ſpeakeſt right <hi>(ſaith he)</hi> and I pray thee alwaies addreſs thy ſelf to me with like ſpeeches; and while my ſickneſs continues, depart not from me day nor night: Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſe me now that thou wilt keep a chearful countenance, and that thou wilt ſpeak no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing to me but what may adminiſter joy and ſupport to
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:204449:15"/> me; although I fear not death, yet I fear the tryal of thoſe pains which I have al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>waies had a very ſharp feel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of.</q>
               </p>
               <p>Then ſuddainly turning his ſpeech unto God, he ſaid: <q>Great God! thou art my Father, thou haſt given me both Life, and a new Life, thou haſt taught me from my youth, and I have declared thy won<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derful works, forſake me not now in my old age: Hither<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to through thy peculiar fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vour thou haſt preſerved me ſound in my body; and my faculties and the functions of my mind have not been impair<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed; ſo that a little before I was oppreſt by this diſeaſe, I found my ſelf as apt and ready for the exerciſe of my Vocation, as in my Flouriſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing Youth: O Lord God! if
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:204449:15"/> it be thy will that I ſhould longer attend upon thy ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vice, thou canſt aſſwage my diſeaſe in one moment: but if thou haſt decreed other<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe, lo here is thy Servant; <hi>thy will be done:</hi> This one thing I begg with moſt in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward affections, that thou wilt make me conformable to thy good will: Let not thy good Spirit depart from me, that in this conflict thy ſtrength may make me a Conquerour: Accompliſh this, O Lord, for thine own ſake: And ſeeing thou haſt imployed me in thy work, grant that I may die an honourable death, and ſuch as may be an example unto others: That I may ſtand faſt in that ſound Doctrine which I have taught, and may make a good confeſſion thereof before wit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſes, that thereby thy Church
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:204449:16"/> may be both inſtructed and edi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fied. Let me apply to my ſelf by a lively Faith all the Promiſes of the Goſpel, and let them put forth their efficacy in me, un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to my joy and eternal conſola<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, that nothing in the world, neither affliction, nor diſtreſs may ſeperate me from thee, or cauſe me to doubt of thy love and favour. Thou know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſt my weakneſſes and infirmi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties; permit not the grievouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs of my pain to caſt me into impatience or murmuring: ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther make my pains tolerable, or furniſh me with fortitude and conſtancy ſufficient to bear them: That I may not offend with my Tongue, keep thou the door of my lips.</q>
               </p>
               <p>§. 6. The remainder of the day was taken up with pains, the uſe of Remedies, and the
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:204449:16" rendition="simple:additions"/> Viſits of Friends: when the night came on, he earneſtly intreated Mrs. <hi>Rivet</hi> his wife, that ſhe would retire her ſelf into the next Chamber; not only be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe ſhe was afflicted with a vehement Cough, but alſo that he might remove her from the grievous ſight of himſelf when tormented with his pains; and becauſe he found his tender affections more moved at the ſight of her, than any other perſon. So none remained with him but his Neece Mrs. <hi>Mary Moline,</hi> and two of the houſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hold ſervants. But who can particularly relate the ſpeeches which he uttered, and in a manner poured forth that night and the day following? (which was Thurſday <hi>Decemb.</hi> 29.) with an Affection and Order in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>expreſſible, breathing from his Heart nothing but Repentance,
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:204449:17"/> Faith, Charity, and holy Zeal! In a word, he implored the mercy of God with the Great<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſt ſelf-denial, and abaſement of Soul, confeſſing himſelf to be a miſerable ſinner, and caſting away all confidence in any good thing which he had done in his life; yea ſpeaking of that with great very contempt, he ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuſed his own defects, and aſcri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bed unto God the Glory of his good works; often repeat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing ſuch expreſſions as theſe.</p>
               <p>
                  <q>It is God that hath wrought the work for me: Shall I al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge or plead my own Righ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teouſneſſes before him? Far be that from me: If I ſhould juſtifie my ſelf, my own mouth would condemn me; I will rather open my ſin before him, in a moſt hum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble confeſſion of it, and pray
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:204449:17"/> that he will increaſe in me the Grace of true Repentance; yea let him wear out this body with ſorrow, it mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters not; ſo he give to me a broken and a contrite Heart, which is a ſacrifice accepta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble to himſelf; As for my part, I do moſt willingly of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fer up my ſelf: Accept O Lord this imperfect Sacrifice, and ſupply the defects there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of by the perfect Righteouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs of that great high Prieſt who through the eternal Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit offered himſelf unto God without Spot, Let me be accepted as a living Sacri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fice, holy, and well-pleaſing unto God, which is our rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſonable ſervice. Crucifie, O Lord, this old man, that the bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy of ſin may be utterly deſtroyed, and I may riſe again unto a new life: <hi>The</hi>
                     <pb n="22" facs="tcp:204449:18"/> 
                     <hi>wages of Sin is death, bu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>
                     </hi> 
                     <note place="margin">Rom. 6. <hi>ult.</hi>
                     </note> 
                     <hi>the Gift of God is Eterna<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap> life by Jeſus Chriſt our Lord</hi>
                  </q>
               </p>
               <p>Then repeating the word <hi>Gift</hi> he added:<q> It is meer Grace not of Works, but of him that calleth; <hi>Who ſhall la<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>
                     </hi> 
                     <note place="margin">Rom. 8. 33.</note> 
                     <hi>any thing to the charge of God elect? It is God that juſtifieth Who is he that condemneth? I<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap> is Chriſt that dyed, yea rathe<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap> that is riſen again, who is eve<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap> at the right hand of God, wh<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap> alſo maketh interceſſion for us.</hi>
                  </q>
               </p>
               <p>Then after a little interrup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of his diſcourſe, by a ſhor<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> ſleep; he thus proceeded.</p>
               <q>
                  <p>I am God's and he wil<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> ſave me; he hath honoure<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> me with an holy Calling; and hath not ſuffered his gif<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> to be altogether uſeleſs in me as to the Edification of hi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>
                     <pb n="23" facs="tcp:204449:18"/> Church: As to my ſelf, I can moſt truly affirm, that I have not ſerved him for filthy Lucre, but with a ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cere heart; and that I was my ſelf firſt perſwaded of the truth of the Goſpel, and experienced the efficacy there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of, before I preached it to others,</p>
                  <p>I taſted the good Word of God, which by it's power pierceth even to the dividing aſunder of Soul and Spirit, and is a diſcerner of the thoughts and intents of the heart. Thou haſt known my heart, O Eternal God! thou know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſt that I am not aſhamed of the Goſpel of Chriſt, but have eſteemed it my only honour to ſerve thee; and that I have delighted my ſelf in the pleaſure of obeying thy will! Such was thy good<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:204449:19"/> unto me! I truly and humbly acknowledge, that whatſoever good was in me, flowed from thy Grace; bu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> my defects ought to be aſcri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bed to my inbred Corrup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion: <hi>Alas!</hi> I acknowledg<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> this with humble and ſeri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous repentance; how oft hav<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> I ſinned in ſo holy a Charge not only by omitting man<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> things which I ought to hav<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> done, but alſo by doing ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny things amiſs! How of have I offended through neg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligence, and ſlackneſs! Long ſince had I been caſt off, wer<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> it not that I had to do wit<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> ſo good a Lord, who hat<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> born with me, and hath bee<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> ſo gracious to me as no<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> to exact a ſevere account o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> my Words and Works! <hi>Alas<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
                     </hi> O Lord my God! Enter no<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> into Judgment with thy ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vant,
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:204449:19"/> for in thy ſight ſhall no man living be juſtified. Let me be found not having mine own Righteouſneſs, but the Righteouſneſs of thy Son, for the ſake of which, I beg thy favour. Pardon, O my God, Pardon the Iniquity of thy Servant, who is devoted to thy Fear: I refuſe not thy diſcipline, I know it is neceſſary; only this I earneſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly beg, that it may turn to my Salvation: Chaſten me, O Lord, but in meaſure, leſt thou bring me to nothing: Let not my tryal exceed my ſtrength, leſt I Sin through Impatience, and become a Scandal to thoſe I ſhould edifie. O let me never break out in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to a murmuring complaint: O how light is this chaſtiſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, if compared with my fault! What are theſe tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poral
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:204449:20"/> pains, in compariſon with thoſe Eternal torments from which I am redeemed by him that poured out hi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> Soul upon the Croſs for me! <hi>For Me!</hi> This is the languag<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> of Faith, which makes a par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticular application of Gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral Promiſes. <hi>This is a faith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful ſaying, and worthy of a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>
                     </hi> 
                     <note place="margin">1 Tim. 1. 15.</note> 
                     <hi>acceptation; That Jeſus Chriſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap> came into the World to ſav<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap> ſinners, of whom I am Chief</hi> Lord, I believe, help tho<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> mine unbelief: Turn tho<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> me, and I ſhall be turned in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deed: Seal all thy Promiſe in my Soul: Cauſe in the in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moſt of my heart a lively per<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ception of thoſe ſweet word<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> 
                     <hi>My Son, be of good comfor<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap> thy ſins are forgiven the<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>
                     </hi>
                  </p>
               </q>
               <p>With ſuch holy Meditatio<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> and ſpeeches as theſe, was th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> Thurſday night paſſed over.</p>
               <pb n="27" facs="tcp:204449:20"/>
               <p> §. 7. On Friday morning, <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Dec.</hi> 30.</note> Mrs. <hi>Rivet</hi> his Wife, put him in mind of ſending one to the <hi>Hague</hi> for his Son: <hi>By all means</hi> (ſaid he) <hi>that ought to have been done ſooner;</hi> and then gave or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der himſelf concerning it. About Nine of the Clock he was vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſited by <hi>Reneſſius</hi> a Doctor of Divinity, and Paſtor of a <hi>Dutch</hi> Church; who in the Latine Tongue ſaluted him after this manner: <hi>Moſt excellent man, how do you?</hi> To whom he anſwer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed in the ſame Language: <q>I am yet ſtrong, neither doth my Speech fail me; but that paſſage in my bowels is not yet opened, and unleſs that be opened, I ſee I muſt make my paſſage another way, even that which the Eternal God hath ſet before me from my Infancy: I ſhould be the
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:204449:21"/> moſt ungratefull of men, if I ſhould not acknowledge the mercy of God towards me, who hath ſo wonderfully preſerved me even from my Cradle: </q> Then rehearſing his deliverance from a very dange<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rous <note n="*" place="margin">
                     <hi>Viz.</hi> A fall where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by his life was in graet hazard.</note> accident that befell him in his Infancy, through the negligence of the Maid; he added,</p>
               <p>
                  <q>From that time my Mothe<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> conſecrated me unto God and he abundantly bleſſed me all my life-time, and the whole Family: And there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore I place all my hope in the goodneſs of God, being ready either to live or to dye. I have alwayes thought, tha<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> either this diſeaſe would be my death, or elſe the Stone, for I have ſcarce ever been afflicted with any other di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtemper: I pray you to teſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fie
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:204449:21"/> unto all men, that I dye in that Faith and Doctrine, which I have alwayes deli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vered both in Preaching and Writing: And if perhaps in ſome things I have erred, I pray God that he will make perfect all my Imperfecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons.</q>
               </p>
               <p>The reſt of the day was filled up with the Viſits of Friends; for he would have none hindred from coming to him.</p>
               <p>
                  <q>Let all that will <hi>(ſaith he)</hi> have acceſs to viſit me; I ought to give an Example of dying to other men.</q>
               </p>
               <p>With ſuch ſayings as theſe, he filled the by ſtanders both with Conſolation and with Won<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der; while he thus proceeded: <q>Come ſee a man who is an Example of the Great Mercy of God: What ſhall I render unto him? All his Benefits
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:204449:22"/> overwhelm me: He hath ſo diſpoſed my Life, that in my whole Courſe, I have had an healthful Body; he hath heaped upon me both tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poral and ſpiritual Bleſſings: And now before I am ren<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dred feeble or moroſe thro' Old age, he comes unto me, and prevents me; he both calleth me; and cauſeth me willingly to follow him at his Call: And now the end of my Life is within my view, he ſtill affords me the perfect uſe of my Reaſon, that I may praiſe the Holy Name of God in the Land of the Living, and inſtruct my Neigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bour by my Example: Pray for me, my Friends, that this Grace may be continued un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to me till I draw my laſt breath; that he will ſtreng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>then my Faith, confirm my
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:204449:22"/> Patience, and raiſe my Hope; He hath already captivated all my affections to his will; I have caſt the care of me, of mine, of life, and all my af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fairs upon him; Let him do with my body as pleaſeth him, ſo it may but be well with my Soul: There is no going hence without pains; this Fleſh muſt ſuffer, and fall; It mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters not; provided the Soul obtains new ſtrength; and I arrive at a better Manſion than that made with hands; It is that I aſpire to, I lament not the World: I have lived long enough, and have had leiſure to make tryal of all things, and to know that they are <hi>vanity and vexation of Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit:</hi> One thing is neceſſary; To fear God and keep his Commandments, for that is the whole duty of man. And
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:204449:23"/> now there is nothing that I am concern'd about, neither is my life dear unto me, ſo that I may finiſh my courſe with joy, and fulfill the Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſtry which I have received of the Lord; which is beſt done at the laſt: This is <hi>the end,</hi> and this the <hi>mark</hi> which a Chriſtian ought to aim at: The end of this frail life is the beginning of Eternal life: O happy change! Truly I fear nothing; Chriſt is gain both in life and death; he forſakes me not: If he make heavy my bodily pains, yet he in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>creaſeth the joy of my Soul: Come, and I will tell you what he hath done for my Soul; I called upon him, and he inclined his ear and heard me; he hath blotted out my ſins as a cloud; <hi>And as a Father pitieth his Children ſo</hi>
                     <pb n="33" facs="tcp:204449:23"/> 
                     <hi>the Lord pitieth them that fear him.</hi>
                  </q>
               </p>
               <p>His manner was to let no Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſter part from him, before he had prayed with him; <q>Pray unto God (would he ſay) now is the acceptable time.</q>
               </p>
               <p>§. 8. Towards Evening, when the Gentlewoman his wife could not be prevailed upon to with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>draw, and betake her ſelf to ſome reſt; <q>It troubles me (ſaid he) to ſee ſo dear a perſon, and one that I honour ſo much, ſo far in years, and of ſo weak a body, to wear out her ſelf at this rate: </q>But then giving way to her deſire, <q>Seeing thou wilt have it ſo (ſaid he) Tarry; It is a pleaſure to me to ſee thee: The Lord ſtrengthen thee.</q>
               </p>
               <p>The night before Saturday was ſpent in grievous pains,
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:204449:24"/> and in moſt ardent Prayers for the Church of God, for the Princes that were Defenders of it, for the People that lived under their juriſdiction, and for the Paſtors to whom the care of Souls was committed: Speaking particularly of the <hi>States, (viz:</hi> of the <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nited Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vinces)</hi> he ſaid,</p>
               <p>
                  <q>O God withdraw not thy protection from theſe Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vinces, neither remove thy Candleſtick away; Let not thine anger burn againſt them becauſe of that impiety and profaneneſs which hath made too great a progreſs; Rather bow their hearts unto Repen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance, and convert men, that they may prevent thy Judge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments: Let them coaleſce in one body: eſpecially let them be joyned unto thee, with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out whom all union is but
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:204449:24"/> conſpiracy? do thou praeſide in that Aſſembly: bend their hearts ſo, that all their decrees may turn to the good of the Common-wealth, and eſpeci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ally of the Church: Grant un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to them, that with due equity, nobleneſs and gratitude, they may remember that Prince who only remains of the ſtock of his noble progenitors, whom thou haſt made uſe of to ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>compliſh thy work in the midſt of them: Indue this child with the Spirit of thy Fear, of Prudence, Fortitude and Magnanimity; and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liver him from profane men, baſe flatterers, and ſuch ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vants as are enticers unto, and the Inſtruments of Vices and infamous pleaſures; and grant to him ſuch as are faith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful, incorrupt, lovers of Truth and Equity, that by
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:204449:25"/> their means he may learn to diſtinguiſh Vertue from Vice; to ſhun the one and embrace the other: It is time, O Lord, for thee to help.</q>
               </p>
               <p>When the night was ſpent he was exceedingly wearied and tyred out, both with over<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>much ſpeaking, and eſpecially by means of abſtinence from drink, with which he was wont to be refreſhed: for when through the extremity of his thirſt he was forced to take down a little, immediately his ſtomach caſt it back again, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing like a Veſſel filled to the top, that could receive no more. The Phyſitians afflicted his body with the uſe of various Reme<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dies, but he bore all with an even temper of mind; often ſaying,</p>
               <p>
                  <q>I have told you before, that the uſe of theſe things will be to no purpoſe: but 'tis
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:204449:25"/> no matter, I muſt comply with you, do what you pleaſe, for your own Satisfaction.</q>
               </p>
               <p>§. 9. That Saturday he was <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Dec.</hi> 31.</note> mightily enfeebled, and ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times very drowzy: he ſpake but little that forenoon. After<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>noon when divers friends viſit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed him, and were diſcourſing among themſelves of the nature of his diſeaſe, he heard all that paſſed between them in the Chamber (for he was very quick of hearing) and gathered both from their diſcourſes, and alſo from his own knowledge of the diſeaſe he labored under, that his diſtemper was that which Phy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſitians call <hi>Miſerere mei,</hi> which he was not likely to paſs through without very grievous Symp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>toms: ſuch as, a <hi>burning Fe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver, Delirium,</hi> and <hi>vomiting of his excrements:</hi> And thereupon
<pb n="38" facs="tcp:204449:26"/> he began to be afflicted with much ſolicitude, while his mind was intent upon the thoughts of the grievouſneſs of theſe Symptoms: and in frequent Ejaculations he ſent up ſhort and ardent Prayers to God about it.</p>
               <p>
                  <q>My God (ſaid he) have mercy upon me; deliver me from the opprobry which I fear: for thou art gracious.</q>
               </p>
               <p>And ſmiting his belly, he ſaid,</p>
               <p>
                  <q>This is a bag of filth, a ſink, and collection of griefs: But thanks be to my God, that he hath afflicted me in this more ignoble part; my heart in the mean time re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maining ſtrong, and my brain free and clear, ſo that I might have liberty to meditate upon thy power and goodneſs. This favour, O Lord God (which
<pb n="39" facs="tcp:204449:26"/> is invaluable) reſerve for me, That my mouth may utter nothing but what breaths forth Charity, Praiſes, and Thankſgivings: O that it may not be defiled with <note n="*" place="margin">
                        <hi>Viz.</hi> The caſting up of excre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments.</note> this filthineſs. Let this building be brought down where its ruine began, which let me behold as one ſet on high with a conſtant and peace<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful mind, even a mind eleva<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted to ſpiritual things, which with all earneſtneſs I follow after; knowing that fleſh and blood cannot inherit the Kingdom of God, neither can Corruption inherit In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>corruption.</q>
               </p>
               <p>And in the inſuing night he did often inculcate, <q>Who is mortal man that thou ſhouldſt ſo magnifie him, and think upon him! He is like to vani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty: Fleſh, and a wind that
<pb n="40" facs="tcp:204449:27"/> paſſeth away. With how ſmall a thing are the ſtron<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geſt among men caſt down? By a vile excrement, by a little obſtruction, which no Remedies can open! Thou haſt done this, O thou Eter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nal one; Thus it pleaſeth thee; and I would have it ſo too: Let it be done to me according to thy Word: I am in thy fatherly and Gra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cious hands, I fear nothing; Thou art my ſafeguard; and my exceeding great reward.</q> Then he repeated in the He<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brew tongue that ſentence out of <hi>Lamentat.</hi> 3. 24. <hi>Thou art my portion, ſaith my Soul.</hi> And ſee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thoſe that ſtood by him, were alwayes ſpeaking to him of Good things<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <q>Well done, (ſaid he) ceaſe not to ſtrengthen me, unto that end God will ſupply
<pb n="41" facs="tcp:204449:27"/> you with matter for diſcourſe, for he is not only preſent with the ſick himſelf for his aid, but alſo with them that are called to ſuccour him; for he is nigh unto all that call upon him in truth.</q>
               </p>
               <p>Then he again poured forth his prayers for the Church of God; ſaying,</p>
               <p>
                  <q>O Lord, it is thy poſſeſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, which thou haſt purcha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed with thine own blood: forſake not thine own work; let an holy jealouſie be kin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dled in thee, lift up on high the arm of thy power, and bring down the audacious ones, which tyrannize over thy flock; Rebuke thou the negligent, that heal her wounds ſlightly: Reduce into the way thoſe that wander; and ſtrengthen that which is rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy to fall, through diviſion:
<pb n="42" facs="tcp:204449:28"/> Gather both the one and the other to thy ſelf into one body, building them upon the foundation of the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phets and Apoſtles, Jeſus Chriſt himſelf being the <note place="margin">Epheſ. 2. 20, 21.</note> chief corner Stone, in whom all the building fitly framed together, groweth into an ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly Temple in the Lord. </q> And then making a little pauſe, he added, <q>I have been one of thoſe builders; I have brought what I received from the Lord, that I might put to my helping hand with others towards the building of this Temple; and I my ſelf ſhall be a Living Stone in this Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritual Houſe.</q>
               </p>
               <p>He ſuffered no day nor night to paſs over without his Pray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers for the Houſe of <hi>Orange: Tbou haſt afflicted it, O Lord,</hi>
                  <pb n="43" facs="tcp:204449:28"/> (ſaid he) <hi>but we beſeech thee let it not be deſtroyed: Let this</hi> 
                  <note n="*" place="margin">The young Prince born but a little be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore.</note> 
                  <hi>Branch grow up, which if it be thy good pleaſure, may come to be a fruitful tree in it's time: Let all acknowledge that good to come from thee; and that thou alone canſt give both being and well-being: How great folly is it to put confidence in man, and in the Son of man, who is no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing: His breath goeth forth, and then his beſt contrived thoughts periſh.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>§. 10. On the next day, which <note place="margin">1651. <hi>Jan.</hi> 1. Lords-day.</note> was the firſt of the year 1651. when he firſt beheld the light he ſaid,</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>O Lord thou haſt granted un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to me to ſee the beginning of the year: thou haſt meaſured out my time unto the midle of this Age:</hi> Then he asked what hour of the day it was, and what
<pb n="44" facs="tcp:204449:29"/> weather? when it was anſwe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red, that the weather was ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry ſharp and ſevere, he was afraid it might hinder his Son<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> journey to him: Whereupon he addreſt himſelf to God af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter this manner.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>O my God, bring my Son un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to me, that I may ſee him, em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brace him, and bleſs him before I dye.</hi> Then turning himſel<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> to his Wife, he ſaid;</p>
               <p>
                  <q>Doſt think this earneſt de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſire to ſee him proceeds from ſome carnal affection? No<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing leſs! Truly I love no man any more according to the fleſh: I earneſtly deſire his eternal Salvation; and I hope to have thoſe diſcourſes with him which may increaſe his zeal in adorning his <note n="*" place="margin">His Son was a Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſter.</note> ſpiritual Vocation: I have yet ſpirit, and utterance ſufficient for that work. Let none
<pb n="45" facs="tcp:204449:29"/> be hindred from coming to me: It is uſual for a man in my ſtation, by admoniſhing others, publickly to make con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſion of his own Faith: not for the ſake of a little vain Glory, O Lord thou knoweſt: for it little concerns me to be approved unto men, provided I may approve my ſelf unto God: but I deſire the Salvati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of many, and to give teſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mony to the truth of thoſe things which I have publickly taught.</q>
               </p>
               <p>This day alſo was taken up with the Viſits of Friends; and amongſt others that came, there was <hi>Collonel Verneuil,</hi> and ſome more Officers in the Garriſon, of which two or three were of <hi>Poictou;</hi> unto whom he ſaid,</p>
               <p>
                  <q>I rejoyce that I have op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>portunity to make a Confeſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of my Faith before you
<pb n="46" facs="tcp:204449:30"/> that are my Countrey-men; And I pray you to keep it i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> memory, and give teſtimony of it where it ſhall be neceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſary: For you ſee before you<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> eyes a man (weak indeed but) without guile, who ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lemnly proteſteth, That h<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> hath never publiſhed in hi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> Writings, nor taught wit<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> his Lips, any thing that di<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> not agree with the ſence o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> his heart, and the Doctrin<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> which hath been delivered t<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> us by the Prophets and Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtles; which is the ſame wit<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> that which is found in th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> Confeſſion of Faith of ou<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> Churches, in which I hav<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> lived, and in which I pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe to dye. The Lord God Almighty confirm you in that Faith, ſo that nothing may move you from it: <hi>For what will it profit a man, if he gain</hi>
                     <pb n="47" facs="tcp:204449:30"/> 
                     <hi>the whole world, and loſe his own Soul? Seek ye firſt the Kingdom of God, and the righteouſneſs thereof,</hi> and then <hi>all other things ſhall be added to you.</hi> Learn to number your dayes: And get a wiſe heart: Look upon me, and let me be an example unto you: It is but eight dayes ſince I preach<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed to you of Mans frailty, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing my ſelf in health, and live<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly at that time, and now you ſee the truth of what I ſaid, in my ſelf: Certainly what is viſible to us, and ſet be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore our eyes, hath a more perſwaſive power, than words which only beat the ears.</q> And then taking his leave of them, he added, <hi>The Lord deli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver you from the allurements of the world, and give you an in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>creaſe of his fear, and of all ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritual and temporal gifts.</hi> A
<pb n="48" facs="tcp:204449:31"/> while after there came to hi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> the worthy <hi>Snellen</hi> Burgoma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter of <hi>Breda,</hi> unto whom h<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> chearfully gave an account <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> the nature of his diſeaſe, wit<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> the cauſes and conſequents there of; and then ſaid,</p>
               <p>
                  <q>Praiſe be to God who hat<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> given me to know the en<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> of my life: I ſhould be th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> moſt ungrateful of all men, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> I were not contented wit<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> that meaſure and term <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> Life, which he hath afforde<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> me; and if I ſhould not ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>knowledge his great Good<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, and provident care <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> me in the whole courſe <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> my life: Eſpecially I giv<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> him thanks for laying ou<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> this place for me to paſs m<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> old age in, amongſt good me<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> with whoſe kindneſs I hav<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> been refreſhed, and to who<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> for their multiplied favou<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>
                     <pb n="49" facs="tcp:204449:31"/> towards me, I can never make a ſufficient return of thanks: Of your ſincere Affection (moſt worthy Sir) in a ſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cial manner I have had expe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rience, for which I give you my hearty thanks, and in your Perſon to your whole Corpo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration, which I beſeech you to ſignifie to them: and to intreat for me, that they will give me a place of Burial large enough for me, and my wife who will quickly fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low me.</q>
               </p>
               <p>When he had thus expreſt himſelf, he diſmiſſed him with prayers for the welfare of him and his family.</p>
               <p>§. 11. About evening he de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſired to be helped out of his bed, and to ſit in a Chair; where he perceived the ſwel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling of his Belly to reach to
<pb n="50" facs="tcp:204449:32"/> the pit of his Stomach; which gave him apprehenſion that hi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> end drew neer; wherefore ſend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing for Mr. <hi>Dauber</hi> an emine<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> Civilian, he imparted to hi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> his purpoſe of adding a Codi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cil to his Will: And in orde<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> thereto he ſent for the Town Clerk and the two Conſuls, an<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> having fully declared his min<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> to them, the buſineſs being don<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> and ſealed; he began to diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>courſe of another ſettlemen<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> by the reſignation of himſe<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> and his into the hands, an<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> unto the care of God; expreſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing his aſſurance of the bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing of God upon his: and the added,</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>That he did exceedingly re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>joyce, that he ſhould leave behi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> him a Wife excelling in virt<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> and motherly affection to the chi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>
                     <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren of her husband; and alſo <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> Son that was a good man, a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>
                  </hi>
                  <pb n="51" facs="tcp:204449:32"/> 
                  <hi>ſtudious of peace, who would be a Father to the</hi> 
                  <note n="*" place="margin">The Children of one of his Sons that was deceaſed.</note> 
                  <hi>three little ones, whoſe Guardian he was ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pointed by that Codicil.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="51-101" type="pages">
               <p>And for this laſt office he rendred unto them his thanks, and to the Council of the City in general; and in particular bleſſed each of them and their Families. And when they were departed, he went to his bed again; and ſeeing no body ſtand about him but his little Family, he ſaid to his Niece,</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>My Daughter, do not depart from me, but perſiſt with me in the duty of Prayer: do not fear to rehearſe all thoſe words to me which God ſhall ſuggeſt unto thy heart or mouth; this ſweet and pleaſing communication ſhall help to paſs over this night with the more eaſe: And God will be with us, and aſſiſt our good intenti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons:</hi>
                  <pb n="52" facs="tcp:204449:33"/> 
                  <hi>He will help our weakneſſes, and afford us matter of ſupplica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions, and thankſgivings: ſuch diſcourſes are pleaſing unto him; he attends unto them that fear him, when they talk together of thoſe things that belong to the Salvation of their Souls.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>And then as one in a Rap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, he ſaid,<q> My God! thou haſt drawn me, and I was drawn! thou haſt known me from my Mothers womb, with a Merciful and Effica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cious knowledge: thou haſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> called me by Name: thou haſt bored mine Ears, and I was attentive: I have decla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red thy meſſage in the Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gregation, and thy word was ſweeter than Honey in my mouth. Who am I! O God, but duſt and aſhes, an earth<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>en and a frail Veſſel, into
<pb n="53" facs="tcp:204449:33"/> which notwithſtanding thou haſt been pleaſed to pour an holy liquor, and ſeed of im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mortality: Thou liveſt, and thou makeſt me to live; I ſhall not dye, but live for ever, with that <hi>life which is</hi> 
                     <note place="margin">Col. 3. 3.</note> 
                     <hi>hid with Chriſt in God: Bleſſed and holy is he which hath a part in the firſt Reſurrection: over him</hi> 
                     <note place="margin">Rev. 20. 6.</note> 
                     <hi>the ſecond death ſhall have no power.</hi> Behold I am dead; and alſo raiſed from the dead: I live not in my ſelf, but in the life of the Son of God, who loved me, and gave himſelf for me. What ſhould I mention more? I can make no return of thy faithfulneſs to me, or of the benefits thou haſt beſtowed on me: Thou hadſt choſen me, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore thou gaveſt me a being; and it pleaſed thee that I ſhould be born of believing
<pb n="54" facs="tcp:204449:34"/> Parents, and eſpecially of a Mother eminent in Holineſs, who dedicated me to thy ſervice from my tender years: With how many prayers did ſhe ſtir me up to that holy purpoſe! With what care and affection did ſhe inſtill the ſeeds of Piety into me! And the Almighty God who worketh all in all, gave his bleſſing to this diligent nur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, and heard her ardent prayers; and my Miniſtry hath been accepted of him; I am thy ſervant, O my God, thou haſt taught me from my youth; and I have taught thy wonderful works, and thy grace unto this day; for thy gifts have not been without fruit in me: Thou uſeſt weak inſtruments for the accompliſhing of thy work: Thou haſt pardoned, thou
<pb n="55" facs="tcp:204449:34"/> haſt helped me; thou haſt accepted the truth and ſince<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity of my heart: And now, O my God, ſeeing it is evi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dent thou wilt have me re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tire from this valley of Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeries, do not thou forſake me in this laſt and important act: If it be thy will that I dye; that alſo is my will: I am ready, my heart is pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pared: I give thee my heart, for that is it which thou re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quireſt; Let this gift be ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proved by thee; Receive this gift which is thine own, from him to whom thou haſt given all things, who gives himſelf to thee. O Lord, I give thee thanks; thou in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtructeſt me, thou inlighten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſt me, thou talkeſt with my Soul: O Lord thou imbraceſt me in the arms of thy mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy! Grant alſo that I may
<pb n="56" facs="tcp:204449:35"/> embrace thee by a lively Faith, and that I may apply unto my ſelf the Promiſes of the Goſpel, which I have pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſed unto others: let them be Effectual in me, that by them I may be ſupported againſt all pains, yea death it ſelf.</q>
               </p>
               <p>§. 12. Then turning his ſpeech to his Niece, he ſaid: <hi>That I may not tire thee with long diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>courſes, Admire thou the Grace of God towards me, and bleſs him who fortifies me with pati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence: Obſerve my words unto my laſt breath, and commit them to writing as fully as thou canſt, that thereby my deareſt Brother, with others of my near kindred and affinity, as alſo my friends, may be Comforted and Refreſhed:</hi> To which when ſhe returned anſwer; That ſhe was unable
<pb n="57" facs="tcp:204449:35"/> to retain, and commit to wri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing ſuch an abundance of holy ſpeeches as flowed from him, he Replyed;</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Fear not; only do thine en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deavour, and God will help thee: If God give me ſtrength, I will write a ſhort Epiſtle, which ſhall be for a teſtimony that Credit is to be given to thy Relation.</hi> (And he was alwaies wont upon the mention of any thing of this nature, to adde,)</p>
               <q>
                  <p> Not that I would hereby procure praiſe to my ſelf; But I would have it known unto all, That the Religion which I have profeſſed, and taught in the name of God, is the true Religion, and that alone which leads men unto Sal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vation: And particularly, I would have my brother in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formed of that ineſtimable Grace which I have received
<pb n="58" facs="tcp:204449:36"/> of God, that he may be abun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dantly comforted and ſtrength<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ened in his expectation of a bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter life, which I already enjoy: O with how great love have I loved him, and eſteemed him! yea I have loved the gifts of God in him, and ſhal<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> love them to the laſt: I pray God who is the giver of every good gift, that he will fullfill, ſtrengthen and make perfect his own work in him; that he will guide him with his Counſel, and at length ſave and receive him to his Reſt: The ſame prayers I make for my Nephew his Son <hi>Stephen,</hi> that he may be an uſeful Inſtrument for the promoting of Gods Glory, a diligent workman that needs not to be aſhamed, rightly di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viding the word of Truth. O Lord my God, I pray not
<pb n="59" facs="tcp:204449:36"/> onely for my Brother, but for all thoſe in <hi>France,</hi> to whom thou haſt committed the conduct and Rule of the Churches: Bleſs their Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons; pardon their defects; Sanctifie their Gifts: Grant unto them that they may ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riouſly return unto the ſim<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plicitly which is in Chriſt; and that they detract not from the Glory of God, to aſcribe unto man what belongs to his Salvation; He is ſtrong and Jealous. If in my writings I have ſeemed to deal a little warmly with ſome of my bre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thren about their new noti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, I proteſt before God, I was never moved by envy or wrath againſt any one in par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticular, but on the contrary alwayes accounted the men that favoured thoſe novelties, among my friends; And the
<pb n="60" facs="tcp:204449:37"/> more I loved both their Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons and Gifts, the more it grieved me that I could not reconcile their Maxims with the Word of God: I do moſt earneſtly beſeech God, that he will give them the Spirit of Peace, that they may be of the ſame Judgment, and ſpeak the ſame things: And that the love of God may conſtrain them, and gather them into one in Chriſt; <note place="margin">
                        <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>ph. 4. 13.</note> Till we all come unto the unity of the Faith, and of the knowledge of the Son of God, unto a perfect man, unto the meaſure of the ſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture of the fulneſs of Chriſt; That following the Truth in love, we may grow up into him in all things, who is the head, even Chriſt.</p>
                  <p>I would have thee with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out delay write unto thy Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther;
<pb n="61" facs="tcp:204449:37"/> he is my Brother in a double bond, I have alwaies eſteemed, and loved him; he hath been an uſeful Inſtru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment for the Glory of God, and I doubt not but he will throughly accompliſh his work in him, to the Glory of his own Name, and his eternal Salvation: I go before him, in a little time he will follow after me: he is almoſt come to the end of his courſe, and there remains but a little time be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore God will Crown his la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bours with an Eternal Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward.</p>
               </q>
               <p>And here again in an extra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ordinary tranſport he brake out into theſe expreſſions: <q> O great and Immenſe Mercy! who can but be rapt into admi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration! He gives both being, and well-being; He beſtowes his gifts, he ſupporteth, he
<pb n="62" facs="tcp:204449:38"/> pardoneth, he worketh in us both to <hi>will</hi> and to <hi>do</hi> ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to his good pleaſure: and when himſelf hath given and wrought all this, yet he gives to us an Eternal Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward! <hi>Amen, Amen.</hi> Be it unto me according to thy word, even according to the faithfulneſs and ſtability of thy Promiſes.</q>
               </p>
               <p>Then turning his diſcourſe to his Niece again; <q>Write al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo (ſaid he) to thy Brethren, That I love them, and that I pray for their Salvation. And thou my dear Niece! I love thee, not becauſe of that near affinity which thou haſt to me, but rather becauſe we both have one God, and one Hope. Thou knoweſt the love and affection which I have had for thee, which hath been a Paternal love indeed,
<pb n="63" facs="tcp:204449:38"/> for a token of which, take thou the Bible which thou ſhalt find in my Study: In ſpeci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cial I recommend to thee my Wife, thy very good Aunt: To thy power Comfort and aſſiſt her: Be unto her in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtead of a Daughter, and help her to digeſt the Sor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>row ſhe will have for my abſence.</q>
               </p>
               <p>§. 13. On Monday Morning <note place="margin">Monday, <hi>Jan.</hi> 2.</note> he deſired to ariſe out of his bed, that he might write thoſe Letters which he had made mention of in the Night: and alſo that he might adde ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing to the Codicil which was annexed to his Will the Even<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing before: His Strength was ſufficient to admit the putting on of his cloaths, and alſo his walking into his Study; where he took the Bible deſigned for
<pb n="64" facs="tcp:204449:39"/> his Niece, and gave it to her himſelf: And to Mr <hi>Dauber</hi> who was then with him, he gave an <hi>Arabick</hi> new Teſtament, and laid by another Book for Mr. <hi>Hulſius;</hi> and one for his Bro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther <hi>Rivet,</hi> to be immediately ſent unto him to <hi>Champuer non</hi> in <hi>France;</hi> unto whom (being returned into his Chamber) he wrote this letter.</p>
               <floatingText type="letter" xml:lang="eng">
                  <body>
                     <opener>
                        <salute>My Dear Brother!</salute>
                     </opener>
                     <p>
                        <hi>I</hi> Now write my laſt to you, with a trembling and dying hand: After the preaching of a Sermon on Chriſtmas day in per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fect health: it is now eight daies ſince I have been afflicted with a Stubborn Conſtipation; and the expulſive faculty is wholly exſtinct in me: Wherefore I am deter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mined by the Grace of God to dye with courage and conſtancy: By the obſtinate continuance, and
<pb n="65" facs="tcp:204449:39"/> pains of my diſtemper, I am quite worn out; and the day of my diſſolution draws near. My Niece <hi>Mary Mouline</hi> ſhall write unto you an account of my laſt Hours, and of that tranquility of mind which God affords to me: I ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pect the coming of my Son, to whom I may commit my Nephews and affairs; He ſhall give you an account of all. Farewel my deareſt Brother! But keep me in remembrance the reſidue of thy life, who have loved thee and thine with a great Charity; Love mine again, as thou doeſt: I pray God to bleſſe thee, and all thine: Once again Farewel!</p>
                     <closer>
                        <dateline>
                           <hi>Dated at</hi> Breda, <date>Jan. 2. 1651.</date>
                        </dateline>
                     </closer>
                  </body>
               </floatingText>
               <p>
                  <hi>He wrote alſo to Mr.</hi> Mou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>line, <hi>his brother by Affi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nity, in theſe words.</hi>
               </p>
               <pb n="66" facs="tcp:204449:40"/>
               <floatingText type="letter" xml:lang="eng">
                  <body>
                     <opener>
                        <salute>My Deareſt Brother,</salute>
                     </opener>
                     <p>IT ſo pleaſeth God, that yo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap> ſhould remain alive after me<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> I now write being upon the bor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders between life and death, after a Sermon preached on Chriſtmas day, which was followed with <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap> pertinacious retention, <hi>faecium in alvo induratarum,</hi> and of the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taining of that load, the Diſſolu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of the body with grievous pains is the neceſſary conſequent. Your Daughter which miniſtreth to me in this agony, hath under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taken to write to you of my con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtancy, and the Grace which God affordeth to me. Live unto the Glory of his Name, remembring me and mine, who dye</p>
                     <closer>
                        <signed>
                           <hi>Your moſt Affectionate,</hi> &amp;c.</signed>
                     </closer>
                  </body>
               </floatingText>
               <p>§. 14. When he had written theſe Letters, he found himſelf
<pb n="67" facs="tcp:204449:40"/> exceedingly wearied, and deſired to be had to bed again. All this day was ſpent in receiving his Friends, eſpecially the Paſtors who were of divers Nations: unto whom he diſcourſed large<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly of ſurrendring up himſelf into the hands of God, and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cited to them a Confeſſion of his Faith, and exhorted them to proceed chearfully in that work which the Lord had com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitted to them: He gladly re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceived thoſe conſolations where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by they endeavoured to aſſwage his pains, and heard their Pray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers for him with like joy, al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>waies adding, That he was much refreſhed by them. All this day the time ſeemed very long to him, while he expected the coming of his Son.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>How fraid am I</hi> (ſaid he) <hi>that I ſhall not ſee my Son! It is the only thing I deſire in this life.</hi>
               </p>
               <pb n="68" facs="tcp:204449:41"/>
               <p> When he was wholly given up by the Phyſitians, and now for many daies had neither re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceived nor voided any thing, a little after Noon, a good man that was touched with our Af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fliction ſaid unto us, That it ſeemed a very wonderful and ſtrange thing to him, that we would ſuffer a man of ſo great merit, who was yet ſtrong and hearty, to go out of the world without trying of any Reme<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dies: adding, That he knew a perſon that was held with the ſame diſeaſe, that was helped by Baths preſcribed by a Chy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rurgeon in the City, who was indeed very skilful in his Art. This perſon therefore was im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mediately ſent for, who when he came, finding the ſick man ſtrong enough to abide the uſe of that Remedy, without delay prepares a Bath, by which he
<pb n="69" facs="tcp:204449:41"/> found himſelf much eaſed, and his pains aſſwaged; and that Monday Night, he had a bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter Night of it than ordinary.</p>
               <p>§ 15. The next day in the <note place="margin">Tueſday. <hi>Jan.</hi> 3.</note> Morning they repeated the Bath, after which a Clyſter was in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jected, which ſeemed to have begun its work: All that were about the ſick man rejoyced, and bad him be of good cou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rage, promiſing his recovery from his diſtemper; And, to ſay the truth, himſelf began, if not to hope, yet at leaſt to think, it might be ſo. In the following Evening the Bath was repeated again, after which being had to bed, he began to ſleep ſweetly: but had ſcarce<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly reſted half an hour, before he was awaked by the pain of his ſide, and a greater ten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of his Belly than before,
<pb n="70" facs="tcp:204449:42"/> and the acceſs of a Feaver. No<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>thing was left unattempted fo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> his relief, by <hi>fomentations</hi> an<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <hi>unctions;</hi> but all was to <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> purpoſe: The complaint of th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> ſick man was increaſed, an<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> he tired out and afflicted wit<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> extraordinary reſtleſneſs. An<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> then his Niece perceived tha<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> there was ſomething elſe trou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bled him more than the pain of his Body; for he remaining ſilent, groaned forth moſt bit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter ſighs, whereas before the more he was tormented with pain, the more ardently did he uſe to pour out his prayers to God: It was Supper time when ſhe was left with him alone, and then with a mournful voice he asked,</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Who is there, is any Stranger preſent?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>And when his Niece had told him, No: ſhe asked him,
<pb n="71" facs="tcp:204449:42"/> Whence doth this unuſual diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quietude proceed? you ſeem to me to ſuffer ſomething extra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ordinary; what is become of that chearfulneſs through which you were wont to paſs through your pains with the greateſt Joy?</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Alas!</hi> (ſaid he) <hi>He is de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>parted from me that made glad my Heart: I have grieved that Holy Spirit the Comforter, who had filled my Soul with Peace and Joy; I have been ſo wretched and unhappy as to give ear to thoſe who ſpake unto me of my returning into this World: I have been tickled with the deſire of living: And how could ſuch a thing poſſibly be, after the fruits of the Heavenly Canaan had been taſted by me, and I had by faith taken hold of Supernatural good things? What is now neceſſary</hi>
                  <pb n="72" facs="tcp:204449:43"/> 
                  <hi>to be done? Whither ſhall I go<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> If I ſpeak, he anſwers not; ye<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> he hath taken from me the pow<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>er of ſpeaking: Ah, ſad change! An holy fire had kindled my me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ditation, but now vain thought<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> hurry me: I cannot get out of my mind an old</hi> Satyr, <hi>and ſuc<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> like trifles. Thus while I am <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> deaths door, I go backwards.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>And here caſting his arm<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> about her neck, he thus pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceeded:</p>
               <q>
                  <hi>My Dear Niece, help <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>e continue to diſcourſe of Go<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap> things with me: Call upon th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> Comforter to return, and rene<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> that excellent work which h<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> had advanced in me. O Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turn! Return! Confirm me wit<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> thy ſtrength, before I go hence, and be ſeen no more.</hi>
               </q>
               <pb n="73" facs="tcp:204449:43"/>
               <p> §. 16. Then ſhe ſuggeſted to him thoſe places of Scripture which by the Divine aid were brought to her mind; in anſwer to which, every moment he in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terpoſed thoſe words, as made it evident that his Soul which before was ſinking under its bur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>then, began to gather ſtrength &amp; Comfort again. He had ſcarce been a quarter of an hour in that Conflict, before he fell in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to a Swoon; which occaſion<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed the haſty calling in of his Son, who was come to him but that Morning; and when this ſinking fit was over, there appeared in him again the ſame Tranquility and Chearfulneſs of Countenance as formerly: And ſeeing thoſe of his own Houſhold, with ſome Friends that uſed to aſſiſt him, and watch with him by turns, in
<pb n="74" facs="tcp:204449:44"/> the next Room, he attentive<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly fixed his eyes upon each of them; and firſt Addreſſing him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf to his Wife:</p>
               <p>
                  <q>Farewell (ſaid he) my deareſt Yoke-fellow! We have lived together in Peace for thirty Years; and I thank thee for thy help, which hath been a great Comfort unto me; for I did caſt all Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>meſtick cares upon thee: Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinue I beſeech thee to <note n="†" place="margin">They were his Children by a for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer Wife, for he had none by her.</note> love my Children with that Pi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous Affection which hither<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to thou haſt had for them.</q>
               </p>
               <p>Then turning his Speech to his Son, he ſaid, <q> And thou my Son! Love and Honour this deareſt Companion of my Life, the Partner of all my Joys and Sorrows, which hath done the Duty of a Mother toward thee; this I deſire of thee, and this I command thee,
<pb n="75" facs="tcp:204449:44"/> as thou expecteſt a bleſſing from God upon what I have gotten by my labour, divide it between you without quar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>relling or contention, accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to what is juſt and right; Manage all thy Affairs with all Lenity and Chriſtian Pru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence; eſpecially purſue Peace, O <hi>Frederick!</hi> (for that was his Sons Name, to which he alluded) <hi>Be rich in Peace.</hi>
                  </q>
               </p>
               <p>Then taking hold of both their Hands, and joyning them together:</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Promiſe me,</hi> (ſaith he) <hi>that you will maintain an holy and mutual friendſhip with each other.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Which when they had both moſt ſolemnly Promiſed to do.</p>
               <p>
                  <q>I believe you (ſaid he) for I have no cauſe to doubt of your Sincerity; I know that you fear God, and that my laſt Commands will be
<pb n="76" facs="tcp:204449:45"/> of great weight to you; even as I pray God that he will make my Bleſſing effectual upon you:</q>
               </p>
               <p>Then turning to his Wife, he ſaid:</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>The Lord Bleſs thee my dear Love, and ſtrengthen thee; he i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> an Husband to the Widdow, an<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> a Father of the Fatherleſs.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>And to his Son,</p>
               <p>
                  <q>The Almighty Father bleſs thee, my Son, guide thee in al<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> thy wayes, enrich thee with all Chriſtian Virtues, and plen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tifully make thee to abound in all Spiritual and Tempo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral Bleſſings; regard not th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> world nor its deceitful hopes for the world paſſeth away, and the Luſt thereof; place all thy Felicity in the Bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing of God: be ſtrong in Faith, and prepared unto every good work. Let the
<pb n="77" facs="tcp:204449:45"/> Peace of God dwell in thee, and make thee Peaceable and kind: Thoſe Infants which I commend unto thee, and commit to thy truſt, will be proper Subjects for thee to exerciſe thy Charity upon. I appoint and ſet thee over not only that little Porti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on which I leave them, but eſpecially their Perſons, that thou mayeſt take care of their Inſtruction and Education in Piety and Virtue; that they may be fitted for that Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vice of God, which their Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture and Ingenie renders them capable of, and eſpecially may apply themſelves to the Worſhip of God.</q>
               </p>
               <p>And then taking hold of the hand of the eldeſt of the Chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren, he ſaid,</p>
               <p>
                  <q>Farewell dear Child, the Lord make thee a good and
<pb n="78" facs="tcp:204449:46"/> a Pious man, that thou may<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>eſt fill up the place of thy Father and Grandfather: He beſs thee abundantly, and make thy Studies proſperous unto his Glory; which he will do if thou diligently call upon him, and if thou Stu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy to be Diligent, Sober, Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deſt, and humbly Obedient unto God and thy Superi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ours, thy Unkle in particu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lar, which will be inſtead of a Father to thee. Give due Obedience and Honour unto thy Mother; Love thy Bro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther and Siſter, and with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>draw thy ſelf from the Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pany of young Perſons who will entice thee unto Vice.</q>
               </p>
               <p>And unto his Niece he thus ſpake:</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Farewell my dear Niece, the Lord bleſs thee! We have a</hi>
                  <pb n="79" facs="tcp:204449:46"/> 
                  <hi>Kindred in the Heavens which will endure for ever.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>§. 17. Now when we thought this night would be his laſt, the principal of his Friends were called to him, and amongſt them Mr. <hi>Hulſius,</hi> and as they ſtood about his Bed, he atten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tively beheld them, and diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>courſed of his Departure at hand, and his diſpoſition to give up himſelf to the Will of God, with a joyful and free Soul. He exhorted each of them according to their re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpective Condition in regard of Age, Sex, or Quality, and bleſſed each of them and their Families.</p>
               <p>Then again ſpeaking to his Son, he ſaid,</p>
               <p>
                  <q>My Friend! Thou loſeſt at the ſame time both a Maſter and a Father; but if the Fear
<pb n="80" facs="tcp:204449:47"/> of God bear rule in thee, God will ſupply the place of both: Far be it from me to diſtruſt his Grace for the future: I caſt all my Cares upon him, and give up my ſelf and mine, my Life and affairs into his hands.</q>
               </p>
               <p>Then he uttered in French Metre the words of the Pſal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſt to this ſence.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nto whom ſhall I go for help, O Lord, and in whom is my hope? truly in thee.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>I am full of dayes: I deſire to be Diſſolved and to be with Chriſt. It is enough, O Lord! Receive now my Soul: I commit this Bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy to the Earth, but I commit my Spirit into the hands of God who gave it.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>And in a Paroxyſme of Pain he ſaid,</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>My God, I know this Taberna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cle cannot be diſſolved without</hi>
                  <pb n="81" facs="tcp:204449:47"/> 
                  <hi>pain, yet my heart is lively, and I have ſtill ſtrength to bear my pains. O Lord, help mine Infir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mities; depart not far from me in the day of my Sorrow:</hi> Say unto my Soul, I am become thy Salvation.</p>
               <p>This laſt he rehearſed in the French Metre, and then repeat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed in Hebrew, from <hi>Pſal.</hi> 16. 5.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>The Lord is the Portion of my Inheritance.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>§. 18. From that Night for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward it was obſerved, when any one diſcourſed to him of Repentance, and of the Grace of God in forgiving ſins, he was wont to anſwer:</p>
               <p>
                  <q>As to this point, I am aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſured that I am reconciled, and cleanſed from my ſin, by the precious blood of my Redeemer; God hath ſpoken, and made known to me al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ready
<pb n="82" facs="tcp:204449:48"/> that my Sins are blot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted out; I now taſte this bleſſedneſs, <hi>Bleſſed is the man</hi> 
                     <note place="margin">
                        <hi>Pſa.</hi> 32. 1.</note> 
                     <hi>to whom the Lord imputeth not Sin: There is no Condem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nation</hi> 
                     <note place="margin">
                        <hi>Rom.</hi> 8. 1.</note> 
                     <hi>to them that are in Chriſt Jeſus:</hi> He is come unto me according to his great Mercies, and draweth me, and I willingly follow him; He leſſens my bodily Pains, by increaſing the joy of my Soul; he ſatisfies my thirſt for him with the dew of his Grace: Behold I am ſatiated, I am inriched; <hi>Man lives not by bread alone, but by every word that proceedeth out of the Mouth of God: The Kingdom of God is not</hi> 
                     <note place="margin">
                        <hi>Rom.</hi> 14. 17.</note> 
                     <hi>Meat and Drink, but Righte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſneſs and Peace and Joy through the Holy Ghoſt:</hi> I am fed by my Saviour, whoſe <hi>Fleſh is Meat indeed,</hi> and his
<pb n="83" facs="tcp:204449:48"/> 
                     <hi>Blood is drink indeed;</hi> and as he is the true quickening Bread which came down from Heaven, ſo he that eateth him, ſhall live by him: And therefore I live: It is now two dayes ſince I have lived not an Animal Life, but I live that Life which I ſhall eternally Live in the Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vens.</q>
               </p>
               <p>That night he made a long and ardent Prayer, the great<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſt part of which is ſlipt out of our Memory: In general he Prayed for all men, and bewail<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed the Corruption of Mankind.</p>
               <p>
                  <q>Alas! O Lord (ſaid he) this is the laſt time; there is ſcarce any Faith in the Earth; Men of Veracity are hardly to be found: One ſpeaks to another, yea to his Friend, fraudulently and with a double heart. Alas! Wo
<pb n="84" facs="tcp:204449:49"/> is me, that I dwell in the Tents of <hi>Kedar,</hi> with thoſe that hate Peace. Thou haſt made Peace in thy high pla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces; Thou giveſt Peace, but not ſuch as the World giveth; Wherefore my Heart is not afraid: The Spirit which thou haſt given me, is the Spirit of Power, of Love, and a ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>date mind.</q>
               </p>
               <p>§. 19. On the Wedneſday <note place="margin">Wedneſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>day, <hi>Jan.</hi> 4.</note> morning he found himſelf much wearied and enfeebled, partly by the Pains he had endured, and partly by his much and earneſt ſpeaking. Both we that were about him, and himſelf, were all of the mind that his laſt hour was approaching; for which reaſon he ſpake as follows.</p>
               <p>
                  <q>Again I bid you Farewell, my Friends; Obſerve me, and
<pb n="85" facs="tcp:204449:49"/> continue to ſtrengthen me with your Prayers and Exhor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tations; when my ſpeech ſhall fail, I will endeavour by ſigns to let you know my Faith and Perſeverance; My mind cannot be ſhaken, he that pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerves me is in the Heavens.</q>
               </p>
               <p>When he had again bleſſed his Family and all that ſtood by him, his Speech wholly fail<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed him for a time, ſo that we expected nothing leſs than to ſee him draw his laſt Breath; but being recovered out of this ſinking fit, he began to ſpeak again, and when he ſaw the Chamber full of People, he ſaid:</p>
               <p>
                  <q>How am I Tyred out! will they allow me no time of re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe? wherefore is there ſuch a Company about me? have not I ſpoken enough? why am I not allowed a little Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>laxation,
<pb n="86" facs="tcp:204449:50"/> and one moment o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> Solitude, that I may Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſe with my God?</q>
               </p>
               <p>Therefore every one with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>drew according to his deſire, and we were afraid to com<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> near to him, leſt we ſhould moleſt him; but when we heard his Groans, his Niece went in ſoftly to him, and ſaid, <hi>Reve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rend Sir, Would you be without my Company, doth it not pleaſe you that I ſhould any longer at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tend upon you.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <q>Alas (ſaid he) I deſire nothing more; do not go from me, but be thou a Wit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs of my laſt hours: con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinue with me even to the end. It is a great comfort to me to enjoy quietneſs; I cannot bear the ſight of ſo great a Company, eſpecial<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly of thoſe that come out of meer Curioſity: I have omit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted
<pb n="87" facs="tcp:204449:50"/> nothing of what was in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cumbent on me to ſay or do: I leave nothing behind me that is matter of regret to me; I have Prayed for the Peace of mine after my de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>parture, and I believe Peace ſhall dwell among them, and that thou wilt do thy endea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vour that it may, for I know thou art of a peaceable Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit: I am ſatisfied and at reſt: I have no more to do here below, I have waited for thy Salvation, O Lord.</q>
               </p>
               <p>She asked if it would pleaſe him to have his Son come to him?</p>
               <p>
                  <q>Yea, (ſaid he) I bleſs God, and rejoice that I have ſeen him and bleſſed him before I dye.</q>
               </p>
               <p>When he came near to him, he ſtretched out his hand and received him kindly, and then
<pb n="88" facs="tcp:204449:51"/> repeated to him what he had before ſaid concerning his Bro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, affirming,</p>
               <p>
                  <q>That he was a very good man, and one furniſhed with Gifts that are rather ſolid and uſeful, than conſpicuous and ornamental; now ſhall he be the Crown of my Fathers Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mily: I bleſs God that there remains a man therein to Praiſe him both in word and work. The Bleſſing of the God of our Father hath been emi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nently on that Branch of our Family from whence we are ſprung; there have been found therein many good Men who feared God: As for theſe little <hi>Nazarens,</hi> I recommend them to God.</q>
               </p>
               <p>And after a little ſtop, he continued his Speech unto his Son:</p>
               <p>
                  <q>My Son, I now know thee
<pb n="89" facs="tcp:204449:51"/> no longer according to the Fleſh; my Carnal affections are mortified and ſwallowed up in the Love of God: My love towards my Wife and Children is now wholly Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritual; I have Prayed unto God that he will Sanctifie, make thee perfect and glori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fie thee: My Son! Is not my happy departure joyful unto thee? what could'ſt thou with more earneſtneſs have deſired for me than a glorious and happy end after a long and proſperous Life? Bleſs God, through whoſe bounty I am now filled with Joy and Peace. Fear God my Son, for this is the whole Duty of man. In all thy Actions love Righte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſneſs, Sincerity, Peace, and Truth, that my Bleſſing may remain effectually upon thee and thy Nephews.</q>
               </p>
               <pb n="90" facs="tcp:204449:52"/>
               <p> §. 20. This whole day was paſt over much to his eaſe and quiet, none being admitted to diſturb him with their Viſits: He lay ſtill, and was inclined to Sleep; and when he obſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved us to look upon him as if he had been aſleep; <hi>I ſleep</hi> (ſaid he) <hi>but my heart waketh.</hi> And when we asked him ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times how he did, <q>Very well (ſaid he) I feel no pain; I am filled with the Grace of God; I am not ſenſible of cold or heat; I fear no more the inconveniencies of tempo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral Life; the Spirit of God ſtrengthens me, and affords me abundant Conſolations; I have no doubt of my Sal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vation; He hath ſet me on high: He hath hid me in his hiding place: He hath fenced me round about, and hath perfected whatſoever concerns
<pb n="91" facs="tcp:204449:52"/> me: I cannot be troubled any more; I am like a Veſſel fill<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed with pure Water, which no agitation troubles. <hi>It is God that Juſtifies; who ſhall Condemn? it is Chriſt that dy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, yea rather who is riſen again:</hi> The moments of my time are in his Power. I am wholly taken up in the expectation of the decreed hour, when he will ſay, <hi>Come thou good and faithful Servant, enter into the Joy of thy Lord!</hi> O my God, I thank thee that thou haſt given me the Spirit of Hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mility, Sincerity and Truth! I have not been as a tinckling Cymbal: O Lord thou haſt known the ſecrets of my Soul, and my in moſt Thoughts! Thou haſt taught me in the School of true Doctrine, and I have above all ſought the Glory of thy Name: I have
<pb n="92" facs="tcp:204449:53"/> not thought any Virtue or Knowledge to be of my ſelf, knowing that all my Suffici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ency is from thee alone: I have ſlighted that Myſtical Theology which is nothing but Canting, and have adhe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red to that clear, pure and ſaving Truth which is con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tained in the Holy Scriptures. One word of the Son of God who requires the Heart, is of more worth than all thoſe humane Vanities, which are good for nothing elſe but to trouble the Purity of the Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vine Fountains. Suffer not, O Lord, the improbity of men to obſcure the Clearneſs of thy Word, which hath been a Lamp unto my Feet and a Light unto my Path; yea, it ſtill affords a Light unto me, and guideth me in the dark Paths of the Shadow
<pb n="93" facs="tcp:204449:53"/> of Death. O Lord, I have been jealous for thee, and have mourned in ſecret for the Wickedneſs of ſome, and the audacious Hypocriſie of others, who have Aſſembled themſelves to pull down what thou hadſt built up by thy Mercies. There yet remain Pious Souls who love the Peace of <hi>Zion,</hi> and mourn under theſe Confuſions; hear their Prayers: In particular have Mercy on thoſe moſt flouriſhing Iſlands where ſo much of the Blood of thy Martyrs hath been ſhed; turn the People in them to thy ſelf, and to their King; give thy Judgments unto that poor Prince, and make him wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thy to have his juſt Prayers heard; Give the Spirit of Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deration and Wiſdom to his own Nation, who have ſent
<pb n="94" facs="tcp:204449:54"/> for him, that they may re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quire nothing of him, but what is weighed in the Ba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lance of Juſtice.</q>
               </p>
               <p>Theſe Diſcourſes being began towards Evening, were conti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nued till it was Night; which he perceiving and wondring at himſelf, ſaid,</p>
               <p>
                  <q>And am I yet alive, and thus able to ſpeak? God hath done it, he endues me with new Strength that I may glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rifie him, and extoll his holy Name. O Lord, I wait for the moment which thou haſt determined, I believe, I per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſevere; I am not troubled: The Spirit of God witneſſeth with my Spirit that I am a Child of God: O Lord thou haſt known me throughly; I am thy Servant; help all mine Infirmities; perfect thy work in me: Patience and
<pb n="95" facs="tcp:204449:54"/> Hope make not aſhamed; the Love of God is in me, even that Love whereby I earneſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly deſire the Salvation of all, yea of thoſe which have of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fended me without Cauſe; I forgive them, and Pray for them; There is no bitter Gall in me, for God hath cauſed all bitterneſs to paſs from me, and hath given true Peace in me; for I roll my ſelf upon him.</q>
               </p>
               <p>§. 21. On Thurſday morning <note place="margin">Thurſday, <hi>Jan.</hi> 5.</note> turning his eyes towards the light, he ſaid,</p>
               <p>
                  <q>It is day light: Shortly I ſhall no more know the dif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ference of Day and Night; I am come to the Eve of that great and eternal day, and am going unto that Place where the Sun ſhall no more give light: God will be an
<pb n="96" facs="tcp:204449:55"/> everlaſting Light unto me and already O Lord thou ſend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſt the Rayes of that Light in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to my Soul, and openeſt mine eyes that I may perceive them. O how powerfully doſt thou work in me! while this Old man dyes and decayes, thou putteſt on me the New man, which is renewed in Know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge after the Image of him who Createth it; that is live<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, ſeeth, heareth and walk<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth with enlarged ſteps; it deſires nothing more than an outlet into perfect Liberty: Deliver me from this Priſon, that I may celebrate thy Name; Yet neither do I ſo contemn this Body, as not to think of its Reſtauration; for I know thy dead ſhall live, yea, my dead Body: It is ſown in Corruption, it ſhall be raiſed in Incorruption; It
<pb n="97" facs="tcp:204449:55"/> is ſown a vile body, but it ſhall riſe again in glory; It is ſown in weakneſs, but it ſhall be raiſed again in pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er: In a word, It ſhall be conformed to the glorious bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of our Lord Jeſus Chriſt, who is become the Firſt-fruits of them that ſleep: I ſhall ſee him in my fleſh: My own eyes ſhall ſee him; I ſhall behold his face in righteouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, and ſhall be ſatisfied with his likeneſs when I a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wake. He loveth me with an intire affection; he kiſſeth me with the Kiſſes of his Mouth: He hath removed all fear far from me, and hath filled me with Peace and Joy in Believing. </q>He often re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peated that ſentence, <hi>Amor meus Crucifixus eſt;</hi> that is, <hi>My Love is Crucified;</hi> adding,</p>
               <p>
                  <q>O Love incomprehenſible!
<pb n="98" facs="tcp:204449:56"/> what I conceive of him is be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>yond all expreſſion. Bleſſed be the Lord, who hath di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rected my heart into the Love of God, and the patient wait<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing for Chriſt.</q>
               </p>
               <p>§. 22. This whole day was ſpent in like holy diſcourſes, and the Prayers of Miniſters that came to him, with the Viſits of other Friends. To<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards Evening he found him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf very weak, and had two or three fainting fits, but his ſpeech did not wholly fail in them; ſometimes he would ſay,</p>
               <p>
                  <q>My ſtrength is quite ſpent: I am going hence, Lord meet me; do not tarry; take thy Creature.</q>
               </p>
               <p>Towards the middle of the Night, his ſtrength being a little recovered, he reached
<pb n="99" facs="tcp:204449:56"/> forth his hand to Mrs. <hi>Rivet</hi> his Wife, and ſaid,</p>
               <p>
                  <q>Embrace me once more, my dear Love! I love thee no more after the fleſh, but after the Spirit; as I have alwayes loved thy Better part: I have lived with thee in holy Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cord theſe thirty years: Thou haſt born mine Infirmities, and haſt been an help to me; and God hath bleſſed us toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther: I have taken notice of thy good Infirmities, conjoyn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed with great Piety; and thy Faith, which is not perfect, but ſincere and true. Thou knoweſt (my Love) that God is not a ſevere Judge, but merciful and Gracious; he chiefly requires from us, a recumbence on his Mercy: He is kind and full of Love. Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hold in me an Example of Mercy and Kindneſs, and from
<pb n="100" facs="tcp:204449:57"/> thence gather Confidence that he will follow thee with the ſame Grace; We have an Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lyance in Heaven; Thither the Lord takes me, and he will take thee thither alſo, and ſo we ſhall be together with the Lord for ever. While thou art waiting for that bleſſed hour, he will be thy Husband, Father, Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forter and Defender; and fi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nally will make thee to expe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rience the ſoveraign Effects of his Love. Rejoyce there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore (my deareſt Love) I have prayed for thee. Thy Faith ſhall not fail; God will ſuc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cour thy infirmities, which ſavour of nothing but good<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs. It is that I love in the Children of God, that they acknowledge themſelves to be imperfect before him: God will compleatly per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fect
<pb n="101" facs="tcp:204449:57"/> thee, doubt not.</q>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="101-152" type="pages">
               <p>Then turning to his Son,</p>
               <p>
                  <q>My Son (ſaid he) keep for thy ſelf what is thine; Call upon God as thy Father, for he is the Father of Eternity: Let his fear wholly poſſeſs thee, for that is the principal thing: Seek firſt the King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom of God and his Righte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſneſs; and all other things ſhall be given in over and above unto thee. Take care of my little Children; ſee to their pious Education and Inſtruction in their tender years; Let them not frequent evil Company: My Son, I put confidence in thee, and aſſure my ſelf thou wilt ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerve my commands with all thy power. Let Truth be in thy Heart, Equity and Since<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity in all thy Actions; and
<pb n="102" facs="tcp:204449:58"/> cheriſh Peace and Friendſhip among Friends.</q>
               </p>
               <p>§. 23. Then taking many Friends by the hand that ſtood by him, he ſaid,<q> I pray you love my Son:</q>
               </p>
               <p>And then turning to his Niece,</p>
               <p>
                  <q>Farewell (ſaid he) my deareſt Niece! God will bleſs thee; yea he hath bleſſed thee already; thou haſt mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſtred to thy afflicted and ſick Parent, and in ſo doing thou haſt ſerved the Publick: Let my bleſſing remain upon thee: I know and am ſure that thou ſhalt be with me in the Heavenly Paradiſe, where God hath prepared pla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces for us, before the Founda<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of the World was layd: Thou haſt helped me, and God will help thee: Fear not,
<pb n="103" facs="tcp:204449:58"/> Perſevere with me in the cloſe of my laſt hours.</q>
               </p>
               <p>Then ſeeing Mr. <hi>Fayan le Coq:</hi> 
                  <q>Are you there (ſaith he) my dear Couſin? The Lord bleſs you abundantly, and grant that in the whole courſe of your life, you may walk in his fear; you belong to an honourable Family, which have layd many Obligations upon me; I pray you write to your honoured Mother an Account of my happy Depar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture; and alſo to your Brethren, whom I pray God abundant<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly to bleſs, and give them Peace, and that they may not truſt in the periſhing good things of this World. As for my ſelf; it is long ſince I have turned from corruptible things, and adhered to thoſe that are prepared and laid up in Heaven. Every good and
<pb n="104" facs="tcp:204449:59"/> perfect Gift comes down from the Father of Lights, with whom there is no variableneſs nor ſhadow of turning. My God, my deſire is to thee; My Soul thirſteth for thee as the parched ground: When ſhall I enter in, and preſent my ſelf before the face of God! Come Lord Jeſus; Come! I am in thy Boſom; I am ready when it pleaſeth thee; My Heart is prepared, my Soul is ready: All delay ſeems long to me till Chriſt come; for whom notwith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding I wait without im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>patience. You ſee thro' the Grace of God I am not tired; I wait, I believe, I perſevere: Patience is much better than Knowledge; tho' it delay my Joy, yet it ſets me in the way to it. The ſenſe of di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vine Favour increaſeth in me
<pb n="105" facs="tcp:204449:59"/> every moment: My pains are tolerable, but my Joy is in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſtimable; I am no more vex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed with earthly cares: I have now no deſires but after hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venly things: I remember when any new Book came out, how earneſtly I have longed after it, till it came to my hands, being alwayes de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſirous of learning ſomething New: But now all that is but as duſt: Thou art my All, O Lord! My good is to ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proach unto thee. O what a Library have I in God! in whom is hid all the Treaſures of Wiſdom and Knowledge: I ſhall no more behold things afar off and darkly; I ſhall no more know in part; but I ſhall be filled with the Knowledge of God as the Sea is covered with waters. Thou art the Teacher of Spirits;
<pb n="106" facs="tcp:204449:60"/> 
                     <hi>I have learned more Divinity in theſe ten dayes that thou art come to viſit me, than I did in fifty years before:</hi> Thou haſt brought me to my ſelf, before I went aſtray, and was in the world; but now I am con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſant in the School of my God, and he teacheth me af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter another manner than all thoſe Doctors, in Reading whom I ſpent ſo much time: What Obſcurity is there, and what Conjectures? yea what Vanity in all thoſe things that proceed from an humane Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit? What vaſt ſpaces muſt a man paſs over before he find any fruit in them? But thy Doctrine, O my God, is per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fect, and full of good fruits: My Soul is filled as with mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>row and fatneſs. With my whole heart I renounce all other Knowledge; and cleave
<pb n="107" facs="tcp:204449:60"/> to this alone; Jeſus Chriſt and him crucified: I give thee thanks, O Lord, that thou haſt hid theſe things from the haughty-wiſe, and haſt re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vealed them to the humble. This Body is feeble, but the Spirit is ſtrong and enriched.</q>
               </p>
               <p>§. 24. Then turning again to his Son, he ſaid, <q>My Son! God bleſſe thee more and more; How greatly do I re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>joyce when I behold in thee the Grace of God! It was my great deſire to ſee thee from the firſt day of my ſickneſs. Thou art the youngeſt of my Sons, and thou only art left alive to me upon the Earth: Thou ſhalt be my <hi>Benjamin;</hi> and God will bleſs the Charge I have committed to thee; and will be preſent with thee for thy help therein. The
<pb n="108" facs="tcp:204449:61"/> Almighty God give unto thee and thy Nephews bleſſings in <hi>Iſrael,</hi> and eſpecially ſpiritual Bleſſings, for temporal Bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſings follow upon Spiritual. Praiſed be God that hath made thee a Spectator of my laſt Conflict: It is a Conflict, but yet ſweet, becauſe of the Conſolations of the Spirit of God, which abound in me. Thou haſt ſtrove enough, O my Soul, reſt in God who is thy Saviour.</q>
               </p>
               <p>Then hearing the Clock ſtrike, he asked what hour it was? which when he knew, he ſaid:<q> The Time paſſeth away, and we paſs away with the time; howbeit we are confirmed and ſtrengthened by the Grace of God every hour.</q>
               </p>
               <p>Then ſmiting upon his Breaſt, he ſaid:</p>
               <p>
                  <q>There is Joy within by the
<pb n="109" facs="tcp:204449:61"/> habitation of the Spirit of God in me. O Good God! who am I, that thou ſhouldſt vouch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſafe to come and dwell under my poor roof! So it hath pleaſed thee, O Lord, that thy Spirit ſhould dwell in me to the end; and therefore I have cauſe of rejoycing in earneſt.</q>
               </p>
               <p>§. 25. Thus was the Thurſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>day <note place="margin">Fryday, <hi>Jan.</hi> 6.</note> night paſſed over: The poor ſick man was wearyed, and exceeding thirſty, yet durſt not drink: He ſeemed to be breathing out his Soul every moment, and panted for delive<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance; but the end of his Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>flict was not yet come; there remained ſtill above twenty four hours to be undergone, and thoſe very ſharp. His Son had betaken himſelf to ſome reſt in the morning; and after a while
<pb n="110" facs="tcp:204449:62"/> coming into the Chamber a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gain, his Father ſaid to him,</p>
               <p>
                  <q>A good day to you, Son! I am glad you have taken ſome reſt: Help me a little.</q> Which being done, he added,</p>
               <q>
                  <p>My Son, this duty will be pleaſing to God; I ſhould have reckoned my ſelf happy if in any thing I could have helped my Father; he was a good and a pious man: I had alſo an holy Mother, which deſerved very well of the whole Family; there was in her an holy Ambition and ardent Charity. My Son, how do I rejoyce to ſee thee! I have yet many things to ſay to thee; Remember that thou ſpeak to the <hi>Illuſtrious Prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſes Dowagers,</hi> and tell them that I dye devoted to them in all dutiful affection, and that I recommend unto them
<pb n="111" facs="tcp:204449:62"/> the utmoſt I can the Inſtitu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of the illuſtrious <hi>Colledge</hi> in this Town; which is in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deed the honour of the houſe of <hi>Orange,</hi> and of his memory who founded it, unto whom in my own particular I am laid under very great Obli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gations.</p>
                  <p>That great Prince who firſt called me to his ſervice in his houſe, heaped his benefits up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on me, and (without vanity I ſpeak it) honoured me with his friendſhip; of which he could give no greater Teſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mony than by committing to me the firſt education of his only Son; who indeed was ſnatcht away from us in the flower of his age, when both his Fathers houſe, and the Common-wealth had moſt need of him: Truly he was a Prince adorned with many
<pb n="112" facs="tcp:204449:63"/> gifts, and diſpoſed to receive good things, and to Piety; I believe that God was mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciful to him; and that his goodneſs is not wholly with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>drawn from this noble houſe, to which he hath raiſed up a Son that may ſupply his Fathers place; The Almighty God bleſs and Preſerve that Branch, and Bleſs his Education; and make him to grow in Age, and in Gifts and Graces, that he may be an Inſtru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of promoting his Glory, and an inſtance of his Grace and Favour. I beſeech him alſo to bleſs the <hi>Princeſſes,</hi> his Mother and Grandmother, that their Concord may turn to the Good of the Child and of the State: The Lord guide them in all things with the Spirit of his Fear, ſtreng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>then them in the Faith, and
<pb n="113" facs="tcp:204449:63"/> incourage them unto every good work: I hope they will keep in mind my ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vice and Zealous Affection for the good of their noble Family; But if not, my truſt is in God.</p>
               </q>
               <p>§. 26. After half an hours ſilence or thereabouts, he thus continued his diſcourſe:</p>
               <p>
                  <q>Hear the prayers which thy Servant offers unto thee (O God) for that Child, let him be bleſſed and ſanctified from his tender years, that the corruption of the Age. may not pervert him; Let him live before thee: Let Inte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>grity and Righteouſneſs pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerve him.</q>
               </p>
               <p>He alſo prayed for the La<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy <hi>Electreſs of Brandenburg</hi> and her Siſters, That God would adorn them with all Chriſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>an
<pb n="114" facs="tcp:204449:64"/> and moral Virtues; and b<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> with them to the end of thei<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> Lives.</p>
               <p>But now his oppreſſion was ſo much increaſed, that we could not take the texture of his Meditations; only by his countenance and geſture we might ſee that he prayed con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinually; and ſometimes he ut<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tered ſome words, whereby we underſtood that others had preceded in his Meditation; a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> for inſtance,</p>
               <p>
                  <q>Yea Lord: I believe: thi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> is my joy: God will per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fect his work above all: <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> have no more part in thoſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> things that are done unde<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> the Sun, but I deſire th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> Peace of the Church every where.</q>
               </p>
               <p>Then he repeated in French Metre the 18. verſe of <hi>Pſal</hi> 51. which is in Engliſh Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tre,</p>
               <q>
                  <lg>
                     <pb n="115" facs="tcp:204449:64"/>
                     <l>"Lord unto <hi>Zion</hi> turn thy Face;</l>
                     <l>"Pour out thy mercies on thy Hill:</l>
                     <l>"And on <hi>Jeruſalem</hi> thy Grace:</l>
                     <l>"Build up the Walls and love it ſtill.</l>
                  </lg>
               </q>
               <p>
                  <q>I am of that <hi>Zion:</hi> have pity on me, and deal graci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſly with me. I am ſuffo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cated, I can hardly breath: The Lord brings me down: but he calls my Spirit to himſelf: The greateſt thing by farr is, I have no doubt of my Salvation; the Lord upholds me miraculouſly, to the end that I may edifie others by my example in this laſt cloſe of my life: I am well pleaſed, O my God. Far be it from me that I ſhould murmure. How ſmall are theſe pains in compariſon of
<pb n="116" facs="tcp:204449:65"/> that Grace through which I bear with a quiet mind what<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoever it pleaſeth God to lay upon me; Thou allayeſt theſe ſhort bitterneſſes, with inex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſible conſolations; Thou ſpeakeſt unto my Soul with that ſweet voice which <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> underſtand, becauſe I am of thy Sheep; My ſheep, ſaith the chief Shepherd, hear my voice, I know them and they follow me: </q>To this purpoſe he began to recite the 23<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> Pſalm in Hebrew; <hi>The Lor<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> is my Shepherd, I ſhall not want;</hi> and deſired one that ſtood by to rehearſe the reſt of the Pſalm<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> And the laſt clauſe he pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nounced himſelf from the Ori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ginal; viz: <hi>I ſhall dwell in the houſe of the Lord for ever.</hi> And when he ſaw many at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tending him; he ſaid,</p>
               <p>
                  <q>You have no cauſe to won<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der;
<pb n="117" facs="tcp:204449:65"/> I am able to do no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing of my ſelf: The Lord worketh all in all, that we may be humbled: This is the School of humility; Look upon me, and remember the Grace of God in me; Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſider how he brings me down by his mighty hand, that he may exalt and Glorifie me in due time: The ſuffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rings of this preſent time are not worthy to be compared with the Glory that ſhall be revealed in us: This is my joy to glorifie God in my death; ſweet Death! that is a paſſage unto life eternal. O God ſtrengthen the Soul of thy Servant, that he may a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bide conſtant and invincible unto death: I hope the Combat will not continue long; Bring to paſs, O Lord, that the End may Crown the Work.</q>
               </p>
               <pb n="118" facs="tcp:204449:66"/>
               <p> §. 27. Amongſt the many Phyſitians that had attended on him, there was one Dr. <hi>Cru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cius</hi> a Roman Catholick, who came this Morning to viſit him, and asked him, if he ſtill continued to be of good cou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rage.</p>
               <p>
                  <q>Yea verily (ſaid he) for I am in God, and God is in me: The Croſs which God hath ſent is ſmall; Every one muſt bear his Croſs, that he may follow Chriſt, who hath ſuffered ſo great things for me, though he deſerved no ſuch ſuffering: This Croſs increaſeth my hope: The Lord is Gracious, who en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>treth not into Judgment with his poor Servant: Chriſt hath dyed for my Sins, and is ri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſen again for my Juſtifica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion.</q>
               </p>
               <pb n="119" facs="tcp:204449:66"/>
               <p> A while after Mr. <hi>Wickelmans</hi> a Dutch Miniſter came, and ſpake to him in the Latine tongue, to whom he anſwered in the ſame Language,</p>
               <p>
                  <q>God Strengthens me, and he will preſerve me from all evil: I give thanks unto my God for that unſpeakable good<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs which he hath poured upon me: he ſuccours me in this work; he hath been alwaies preſent with me, even to this Extremity.</q>
               </p>
               <p>Then the Miniſter repeated to him the words of the Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtle, 2 <hi>Tim.</hi> 4. 7, 8. <hi>I have fought a good fight, I have finiſhed my courſe, I have kept the Faith, henceforth there is laid up for me a Crown of Righteouſneſs;</hi> At which words he cryed out,</p>
               <p>
                  <q>O welcome Crown! there is nothing elſe that I wait for: God dwells in me by his
<pb n="120" facs="tcp:204449:67"/> holy Spirit, which ſhall never be taken away from me: Grant, O Lord, that I may keep thy Commands!</q>
               </p>
               <p>Again, when beholding hi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> pains, he exhorted him to pati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence; he anſwered,</p>
               <p>
                  <q>We cannot, we ought no<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> to reſiſt the will of God: O Eternal Father of our Lord Jeſus Chriſt, I give the<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> thanks for thy exceeding grea<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> benefits, That it hath pleaſe<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> thee, that I ſhould declare thy Praiſe even unto very Old Age; and that thou makeſt me able to perſiſt therein unto the laſt breath of my life.</q>
               </p>
               <p>§. 28. At another hour when the ſame Miniſter viſited him again, and ſaid, <q>You are ſtill fighting the Good fight; </q>he anſwered,</p>
               <pb n="121" facs="tcp:204449:67"/>
               <p>
                  <q>In hope and patience, I am wholly Gods, and Jeſus Chriſt's my Saviour: I believe that he will keep what I have commit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted to him againſt that day: Even ſo come, Lord Jeſus!</q>
               </p>
               <p>And when this Miniſter had prayed with him, he returned him thanks in theſe words:</p>
               <p>
                  <q>I give you thanks for your holy Prayers; I doubt not but God will hear them: God bleſs you; I beſeech him to make you a very power<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful Inſtrument of his Glory.</q>
               </p>
               <p>He alſo added,</p>
               <p>
                  <q>God hath fulfilled all his Promiſes in me; I have ſeen them afar off, I have believed them, I have embraced them; I wait for nothing more but to breathe forth my laſt breath; God poſſeſſeth me al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ready, I feel that: there is nothing wanting, but that he
<pb n="122" facs="tcp:204449:68"/> will give me the wings of an Eagle that I may fly to the Carkaſs.</q>
               </p>
               <p>Immediately he ſubjoyned a verſe or two out of one of <hi>Beza</hi>'s French Poems, to this ſence:</p>
               <q>
                  <lg>
                     <l>"O Holy Word!</l>
                     <l>"With all my Heart</l>
                     <l>"To thee I flye.</l>
                  </lg>
               </q>
               <p>§. 29. Towards Evening the Pangs of death increaſed upon him; The extreme Pains of his bowels, his ſuddain fainting, a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> and other grievous Symptoms, were the indications of ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proaching death: But in this ſtate, and utter decay of th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> ſtrength of nature, his exerciſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> of Faith was ſtrengthened ſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> much the more, and his pati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence confirmed: <q>Mourn no<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> for me, (ſaid he;) Theſe laſt hours have nothing ter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rible in them; The body in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deed ſuffers; but the Soul is
<pb n="123" facs="tcp:204449:68"/> Comforted and filled abun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dantly: The Lord is my Shep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>herd, I ſhall want nothing: His Rod and his Staff ſhall lead me ſafely through this ſhort valley of the Shadow of death: This little cloud hinders me not from behold<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing that Heavenly Light, which already enlightens my Soul. O Lord thou giveſt me light, thou warmeſt me, thou lifteſt me on high, and I gladly follow thee, being carried aloft upon the wings of Faith: The ſharper my pains are, the nearer I am to deliverance. My wound is grievous, but I was ſilent becauſe thou didſt it. Have mercy on me, O Lord! O my God, deliver me! I am impatient of delay: I know that God is faithful, and with the temptation he will give
<pb n="124" facs="tcp:204449:69"/> a way of eſcape, that I may be able to bear it.</q>
               </p>
               <p>When he looked towards his Wife, ſhe thus addreſſed her ſelf to him:</p>
               <p>
                  <q>My dear! I bleſs God, and rejoyce for thee, that I have ſeen ſo much of the Grace of God in thee. </q>To which he replyed,</p>
               <p>
                  <q>Thou doeſt well (my dear Love;) The Lord confirm and ſtrengthen thy joy; Mine is ſolid: I rejoyce that thou ſeeſt the end of my Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſation: Thou haſt known me, and thou knoweſt that I hate Oſtentation; and that more hath been attributed to me by others, than I have be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieved of my ſelf: for I have been conſcious of mine own infirmities, and that whatſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever good might be in me, was not of my ſelf: The
<pb n="125" facs="tcp:204449:69"/> Glory is to be aſcribed to God alone; he hath done the work: Perfect, O Lord, and Crown thine own work! I complain not of my pains; I have not flattered my ſelf in my diſeaſe; for when I was firſt ſeized by it, I was aware that God called for me: Is it not time, my deareſt love? Afflict not thy ſelf: I go before; thou ſhalt follow e're long: Thou haſt afforded me help, and haſt kindly ſuccour'd me; God will bleſs thee, and ſave thee, doubt it not: It hath been grateful to me, and I moſt kindly accept it, that thou haſt had ſo great a Love for this little Boy (pointing to his Grand-ſon,) make proof of thy love to me by loving him; it is a Child void of malice, and I have good hope of him, if
<pb n="126" facs="tcp:204449:70"/> he be well guided.</q>
               </p>
               <p>Then calling the Child, he ſaid,</p>
               <p>
                  <q>Give me thy hand, my Son! See thy Grandfather upon his death-bed: Thou haſt al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ready loſt thy Grandfather by Mothers ſide, who was a pious and upright man; Now thou loſeſt thy Grandfather by Fathers ſide; but thou haſt a Grandfather in Heaven on both ſides, that will never be wanting to thee; I hope my bleſſing will redound up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on thee.</q>
               </p>
               <p>Then taking him between his hands;</p>
               <p>
                  <q>My little Child (ſaid he) Pray to God! If thou do this diligently, thou ſhalt be like a tall and beautiful Tree planted by the Rivers of wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters: Have thou fair bran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches, and be fruitful; that
<pb n="127" facs="tcp:204449:70"/> is, Fear God: Then ſhalt thou bring forth Wiſdom, Prudence, and Underſtand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing. Be thou Good and Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neficent, ſhunning evil com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pany, and God will bleſs thee, thou ſhalt not be forſaken: Behold thy Unkle, which ſhall be to thee inſtead of a Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther; Be obedient to him, and alſo to thy Grandmother, and Mother, whom I pray God abundantly to bleſs with her other Children; that her little Poſthumous Son that bears my Name may in time Repreſent me, yea exceed me.</q>
               </p>
               <p>§. 30. Theſe holy ſpeeches were ſometimes interrupted by a ſhort ſleep, and ſometimes on occaſion of the Prayers or Exhortations of the Miniſters that came to him; He received
<pb n="128" facs="tcp:204449:71"/> them all moſt Cordially; and moſt willingly heard the Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolations that were ſuggeſted by them; And he would alſo return Conſolations to them: He heard their prayers with attention, and when they had done, was wont alwayes to ſay, That he found himſelf much relieved. And then diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſſed them with thanks, gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving his bleſſing to each of them as was proper to their Condition. Towards Supper time, he remembred the noble Virgin <hi>Anna Maria a Schurman,</hi> and ſaid,</p>
               <q>
                  <p>She is a perſon to whom I have alwaies devoted my Affection and ſincere Love: ſhe hath honoured me with her holy friendſhip, and hath called me Father; In teſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mony of my paternal Love, I give her my little Bible
<pb n="129" facs="tcp:204449:71"/> without Points, of <hi>Plantines</hi> Edition, which you ſhall find in ſuch a Place in my Study (directing to the place;) If I had any ſtrength left, I would have written a Letter to her with my own hand, whereby I would have teſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fied to her how much I Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour her, and eſteem thoſe admirable gifts of God where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>with he hath adorned her. But you (my Son) ſhall ſupply this defect, and inform her of my happy Departure; and that I have prayed to God that he will Strengthen her in her ſupernatural Cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling, and beſtow upon her the bleſſings of a long and proſperous Life.</p>
                  <p>What remains? Have I not ſaid all? I have no more to do, but to give up my Soul into the hands of God: Is it
<pb n="130" facs="tcp:204449:72"/> not time? O my God, let it ſuffice! Receive my Soul un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to thy ſelf, O Lord! I yield it into thy hands; thou haſt Redeemed it, O God of Truth: Thou art my hope, and my Confidence from my youth: No care afflicts me; God hath removed from me the Opprobry which I feared; (meaning the Vomiting of his excrements, a ſymptome uſual in his Diſtemper;) He will perfect (and that quickly) whatſoever belongs to his Glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry, and my Eternal Salvati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on: If he make any ſtay, if he deferre my deliverance, he doth it for your Edificati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on and Salvation; Let not my Sorrows be grievous to you, but rather bleſs God who gives me a deſirable plume, and makes my heart joyful in the midſt of my pains:
<pb n="131" facs="tcp:204449:72"/> Rejoyce therefore; and Pray with me.</p>
               </q>
               <p>§. 31. When he had asked what a Clock it was, he ſaid to his Wife and his Son,</p>
               <p>
                  <q>I pray you take ſome food; I am not yet fully come to the end of my Work, I want nothing, and my Niece ſhall tarry with me, and take ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing here to refreſh her.</q>
               </p>
               <p>They withdrew therefore in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the next Room, and one brought an Egg to his Niece, which he deſired her to take.</p>
               <p>
                  <q>As for me (ſaid he) my Meat is to do the will of God, and happily to run out the courſe of my life: I am refreſhed with holy and hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venly food: My Father feeds me with that Food which he lately offered to me at his holy Table; I did eat,
<pb n="132" facs="tcp:204449:73"/> and was filled: The true feed<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing is the feeding of the Soul, that which ſuſtains the true Life: As for Corporal meats they are for the belly, but God will deſtroy both it and them.</q>
               </p>
               <p>Then reaching out his hand to his Niece, <q>I Love thee (ſaid he) with a Love whol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly Spiritual, a love of true Cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity and Affection: We will paſs this Night together in holy Meditations, and ſpeak<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to one another in Pſalms and Hymns, and Spiritual Songs, Singing and making melody in our Hearts unto the Lord: I feel my Swel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling to aſcend: I fear that in a little time I ſhall be able to ſpeak no more: do not depart from me; but continue ſpeaking to me what<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoever God ſhall bring to thy Heart and Lips, leſt in my
<pb n="133" facs="tcp:204449:73"/> utmoſt weakneſs my Memo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry ſhould fail me; and I aſſure thee, God will ſuggeſt thoſe things to thee which which ſhall be for my help and Comfort in the time of need: for out of the abun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dance of the Heart, the mouth ſpeaketh,</q>
               </p>
               <p>His Wife and Son being re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turned into the Chamber;</p>
               <p>
                  <q>Pray ye (ſaid he) for me; what a joy is i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> to ſee theſe holy Souls with me!</q>
               </p>
               <p>§. 32. Oft times through the bitterneſs of his pains he brake forth into Cryes, or rather ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dent Prayers unto God; and that frequently, in the words of the Pſalms in the French Metre: as <hi>Pſal.</hi> 141. 1.</p>
               <q>
                  <lg>
                     <l>"Jehovah, upon thee I call,</l>
                     <l>"O haſten unto me!</l>
                     <pb n="134" facs="tcp:204449:74"/>
                     <l>"Lend to my Voice thy Gra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cious Ear,</l>
                     <l>"When I cry unto thee,</l>
                  </lg>
               </q>
               <p>Then adding from <hi>Pſal.</hi> 25. 18. <q>Look upon mine Afflicti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, and pardon all my ſins.</q>
               </p>
               <p>And upon the mention of any Text that ſpeaks of the Remiſſion of ſins, he would immediately ſubjoyn,</p>
               <p>
                  <q>It is done; He hath cau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed mine iniquity to paſs a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>way from me: O Lord, abate and ſhorten my Miſeries; Now is thy time.</q>
               </p>
               <p>And then repeated from <hi>Pſal.</hi> 118. 24.</p>
               <lg>
                  <l>"This is a joyful day indeed,</l>
                  <l>"Which God himſelf hath wrought:</l>
                  <l>"We will be glad and joy therein,</l>
                  <l>"With all our Heart and Thought.</l>
               </lg>
               <pb n="135" facs="tcp:204449:74"/>
               <p>
                  <q>How great is my anguiſh! but how much greater is my refreſhment!</q>
               </p>
               <q>
                  <lg>
                     <l>"An high place and a Refuge ſure</l>
                     <l>"I find the Lord to me;</l>
                     <l>"In day of my diſtreſs he me</l>
                     <l>"Relieves, with rich bounty.</l>
                  </lg>
               </q>
               <p>They continually ſuggeſted to him places of Scripture; un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to which he would return ſuch anſwers as did abundantly ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nifeſt his Godly Ardor, Faith, and Patience; as for inſtance, when it was ſaid to him, <q> God is nigh to all that call up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on him in Truth; </q> Smiting upon his breaſt, he replyed,</p>
               <p>
                  <q>Here he is; here he dwells in me, and worketh power<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fully according to his good pleaſure.</q>
               </p>
               <pb n="136" facs="tcp:204449:75"/>
               <p> Then that place was al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledged, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 15. <q>Death is ſwallowed up in victory: </q>and he added the following words,</p>
               <p>
                  <q>Thanks be to God, who hath given us the Victory through our Lord Jeſus Chriſt.</q>
               </p>
               <p>Again from <hi>Rom.</hi> 8. 30. </p>
               <q>
                  <p> Moreover, whom he did pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diſtinate, them he alſo cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led; and whom he called, them he alſo juſtified; and whom he juſtified, them he alſo Glorified:</p>
                  <p>Even ſo it is! (ſaid he) Grace upon Grace! O lovely Chain! This is a Golden Chain indeed! there wants but the laſt link to compleat the whole in me. O Lord make perfect, and Crown thy work; That I may dye the death of the righteous, and ſee thoſe good things, which eye hath
<pb n="137" facs="tcp:204449:75"/> not ſeen, neither have they entred into the mind of man; Thou giveſt me a foretaſt of theſe ſweetneſſes and refreſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ings, which no words can expreſs.</p>
               </q>
               <p>§. 33. Then Mr. <hi>Hulſius</hi> being preſent, asked if it would be ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceptable to him that he ſhould go to Prayer?</p>
               <p>
                  <q>Yea (ſaid he) Pray; The time requires it.</q>
               </p>
               <p>When he had ended his Pray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er, he gave him thanks; ſaying,</p>
               <p>
                  <q>You have helped me; while you called upon God, I found ſome eaſe of my infirmity: Encourage me! the Race is ſhort: I even touch the bound of my Race; I go on: I ga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther new Strength: I touch the Prize, I take hold of Eternal Life. This body faint<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth: this Tabernacle is de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtroyed;
<pb n="138" facs="tcp:204449:76"/> But there is reſerved for me an houſe in the Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vens, not made with hands: There is reſerved for me in the Heavens an incorruptible Inheritance, that can neither be defiled, nor fade away.</q>
               </p>
               <p>About Midnight his pains increaſed exceedingly, which cauſed him to break forth in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to bitter cries, calling upon God for his help.</p>
               <p>
                  <q>Come, Lord Jeſus! Come! I can bear no more; yet is not my patience loſt, but the deſire of my Soul towards thee, is like that of the dry and thirſty Ground. As the Hart panteth for the brooks of water, ſo pantetli my Soul for thee, O God! O when ſhall I come and appear be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore God! My Strength fails me more and more, but my Soul is ſtrong and joyful.</q>
               </p>
               <pb n="139" facs="tcp:204449:76"/>
               <p> Preſently upon this he fell into a great fainting (which Phyſitians call <hi>Lipothymia)</hi> on which occaſion Mr. <hi>Martin Ly<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dius</hi> a Dutch Miniſter was in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtantly called in. He was one that Dr. <hi>Rivet</hi> had a great af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fection for, and he was daily with him during his ſickneſs; And therefore what paſſed be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tween them two, we will ſet down in <hi>Lydius</hi> his own words, which are as follow.</p>
               <p>§. 34. This Reverend Father in Chriſt required that I ſhould be often called to him in the time of his ſickneſs, having formerly been his Scholar at <hi>Leyden.</hi> When I came firſt to him, he exhorted me with ſweet words to proceed as I had begun: ſaying, that it great<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly rejoyced him to underſtand the Affection which the Church
<pb n="140" facs="tcp:204449:77"/> at <hi>Breda</hi> had for me; Where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore, I pray thee (ſaid he) Give me thy hand; Go on to adorn the ſervice thou haſt un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dertaken. Then he uttered an excellent Confeſſion of his Faith with a ſtrong Voice: in which he ſhewed on what ſtayes the Proteſtant Religion, which he had hitherto propagated both by Preaching and Writing; leaned, for the obtaining of that Conſolation both in life and death, which the miſera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble Papiſts cannot have.</p>
               <p>And when I recited ſome ſelect places of Scripture to him out of the Old or New Teſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, he would rehearſe them again either in Hebrew or Greek. I ſaid, that I doubted not but with <hi>Stephen</hi> the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tomartyr he did already ſee Heaven opened, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> To which he replyed with a chearful
<pb n="141" facs="tcp:204449:77"/> Countenance and Voice, <q> O I have ſeen that a good while.</q>
               </p>
               <p>I excuſed my ſelf, that I could not pray to God with him, becauſe I was a ſtranger to the French Tongue, and the by-ſtanders underſtood not the Latine Tongue; but he ſaid, Pray in that Tongue which both thee and I underſtand; which when I had done, and prayers were ended, he gave me thanks: ſaying,</p>
               <p>
                  <q>The Spirit of God hath ſpoken by thy mouth, and thou haſt exceedingly ſtreng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thened me: I deſire thou wilt alwayes remember me in publick prayers in the Church. </q>The next day be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing exceedingly ill, he com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manded that none ſhould be admitted to him; But when Mrs. <hi>Moline</hi> heard my Voice, ſhe brought me to the bed<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſide,
<pb n="142" facs="tcp:204449:78"/> and he received me with a chearful Countenance; I am glad (ſaid he) that thou art come. I told him, the preſent time required that he ſhould caſt all his cares upon God, and be no more ſolicitous a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout any thing: He anſwered,<q> Yea truly: There is nothing that I am any more Solici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tous about; I only deſire the coming of my Saviour, yea his ſpeedy coming, that I may be looſed from this bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy of Sin, and be with Chriſt who is gain unto me both in life and death; I embrace Chriſt by Faith; I am eve<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> preſſed down, but I am i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> the hand of my Shepherd: I embrace my Saviour Jeſus Chriſt; and do now wholly pant after my God.</q>
               </p>
               <p>When he had ſpoken theſe, and other things of like na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture,
<pb n="143" facs="tcp:204449:78"/> I bid him Farewel: but he again deſired me to pray with him: which being done, with a ſigh he ſaid, <q>O how ſweet is this!</q>
               </p>
               <p>When the fatal day was come, about two a Clock in the Morning, he would have me called, and when I drew near to his bed, he took hold of my hand, to whom I ſaid, <q>Yet a little while, and he that ſhall come will come.</q> He anſwered; <q>And why doth he not come? </q>And immedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ately added, <q>Yea, he is come already.</q>
               </p>
               <p>This I Teſtifie, <hi>Martinus Lydius</hi> Preacher at <hi>Breda.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>§. 35. About three of the <note place="margin">Saturday <hi>Jan.</hi> 7.</note> Clock in the Morning his Wife came near to him, and
<pb n="144" facs="tcp:204449:79"/> beholding in his Countenance the Image of death, ſhe chear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fully ſaid: </p>
               <q>
                  <p>Farewel my dear<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> Go rejoycing into eternal life.</p>
                  <p>Thou ſayeſt true (ſaid he) I go unto my God and your God<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> We are all Gainers: <hi>Amen! A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men!</hi> Farewel my Son! Fare<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wel my dear Niece! Fear not, I have prayed for you; Ye ſhal<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> be happy. Perſevere to th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> end, that none get away your Crown: I go before you, and ye ſhall follow me; you have no cauſe to doubt of it: We ſhall be caught up together to meet the Lord i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> the Air, and ſo we ſhall fo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> ever be with the Lord: I have no more to ſay or do, I am ready, I am prepared; Come Lord Jeſus, Come! re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive thy Creature; I aſpire I hope, I knock at the Gate;
<pb n="145" facs="tcp:204449:79"/> Open O Lord! Open unto thy poor Servant.</p>
               </q>
               <p>His Oppreſſion was mani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſtly diſcerned to increaſe up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on him, and alſo a mortal <hi>So<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>por</hi> or drowſineſs, and Rotling came upon him: The Cham<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber was filled with company; but moſt were of the mind it was not meet to weary him any longer with diſcourſe; ſee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing nothing could be added to that abundant Teſtimony of his Faith which they had alrea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy: Therefore about five in the Morning they all departed, except Mr. <hi>Lydius,</hi> who ſilently waited the laſt ſeaſon of pray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to God for him when he ſhould be drawing his laſt breath. But when it was paſt eight of the Clock, and he diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerned but little change, and found his Pulſe much the ſame, he thought he might abide in that
<pb n="146" facs="tcp:204449:80"/> Agony untill Evening; therefore he departed, promiſing to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turn as ſoon as they ſhould ſend for him. Only thoſe of his own houſe remained with him, who feared to moleſt him by ſpeaking, and were alſo un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>certain whether he could ſpeak, or not, becauſe of his extream oppreſſion, and his lying with his Mouth open. Friends at length prevailed with his Wife to withdraw from the ſight of his laſt Agony; and only his Son and Niece ſtood by the Bed, expecting his laſt breath; yet neither did they think that had been ſo near, as it was. About half an hour after Eight the Colour of his Face was wholly changed, and Convul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſive motions came on: Then his Niece asked him, if he yet had his underſtanding. <q>
                     <hi>Alas</hi>
                  </q> (ſaid he) <hi>ſpeak:</hi> (as complain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing
<pb n="147" facs="tcp:204449:80"/> of their ſilence:) Then ſaid ſhe, I pray you do you ſtill feel the ſence of inward Joy? To which he replyed intelligibly enough, <q>Yea: My Confidence is firm in me. </q> Then making a ſign, That he would be rai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed a little; His Son and his Niece on each ſide enfolding their arms about him, lifted him higher: Then fixing his eyes a while upon them, he ſaid, <q>Help me; I am going.</q> Accordingly, the Lord bring<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to their mind many choice Scriptures apt for the occa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion, they by turns propoſed them to him; And he received them with great joy; adding <hi>So it is:</hi> and <hi>Amen.</hi> Often al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo he would pronounce him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf the laſt words of that Por<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of Scripture which they were rehearſing to him; as in <hi>Pſal.</hi> 36. <q>How excellent is
<pb n="148" facs="tcp:204449:81"/> thy loving kindneſs O God! Therefore do the Sons of men put their truſt under the ſhadow of thy wings: Thou wilt abundantly ſatis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fie them with the fatneſs of thy Houſe, and make them to drink of the Rivers of thy Pleaſures; </q>which laſt ſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tence he rehearſed himſelf in the French Metre. And the ſame he did from <hi>Pſal.</hi> 65. 4. <q>Bleſſed is the man whom thou chooſeſt, and cauſeſt to ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proach unto thee, that he may dwell in thy Courts: We ſhall be abundantly Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tisfied with the goodneſs of thy Houſe, even of thy holy Temple.</q>
               </p>
               <p>§. 36. Then his Son ſaid, <q>I am ſorry that we are alone.</q>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <q>I am not alone (ſaid he) God is with me.</q> Be you then
<pb n="149" facs="tcp:204449:81"/> an Evangeliſt to your ſelf, (ſaid his Son) foraſmuch as you have received the Miniſtry of Recon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciliation, deliver the tidings of peace to your own Soul.</p>
               <p>
                  <q>That I do (ſaith he) my Soul believes. Then fear no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing;He that believes in Je<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſus Chriſt ſhall never periſh: </q> He added, <q>But ſhall have Eternal Life. </q> While prayers were making for him in this laſt Combat with the pains of Death, at the end of almoſt every ſentence he would inter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe ſome word or words, ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſing the ſence of his mind with reſpect to thoſe petitions. As thus,</p>
               <p>
                  <q>O great God, ſend thy Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit of Conſolation; <hi>[he is alrea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy come:]</hi> and give unto thy Servant the ſenſe of thy love, <hi>[that he hath done;]</hi> Give
<pb n="150" facs="tcp:204449:82"/> unto him the Garment of Salvation, <hi>[he hath given it;]</hi> All is well, enter therefore thou good Servant into the Joy of thy Lord, he calleth thee. [At which words he raiſed up himſelf and ſtretched forth his Arms:] Alſo O Lord ſtrengthen more and more the Faith of thy Servant in this laſt agony, let him ſee, let him hear thy voice, let him raiſe up himſelf, and take hold on Eternal Life, <hi>[Yea! I am of good Comfort.]</hi> Let us go to the Throne of Grace, that we may obtain Mercy, <hi>[It is done:]</hi> Leave therefore with a joyful mind this body to the Earth, and yield up thy Spirit into the hands of God, <hi>[who hath gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven it:]</hi> Take hold of the Shield of Faith; yea put on the whole Armor of God: <hi>[I have it.]</hi>
                  </q>
               </p>
               <pb n="151" facs="tcp:204449:82"/>
               <p> Then he began himſelf to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cite thoſe words, <hi>I have fought a good fight,</hi> &amp;c. And when one had repeated what follows, and came to thoſe words, <hi>which God the righteous Judge will give;</hi> he added, <hi>He will do it.</hi> And when one ſaid; <q>Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hold the laſt moment of de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liverance! O God give Wings unto thy Servant; open thy Paradiſe unto him; Let him be received unto the behold<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of thy Face! He added, <hi>With the Spirits of juſt men made perfect.</hi> Let him receive the white Stone, and the hidden Manna; and let him bear his part in that New Song which none underſtands but he that ſings it. To which he ſaid, <hi>Amen!</hi>
                  </q>
               </p>
               <p>In theſe laſt Moments there came in ſome of his Friends who were witneſſes of his hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>py
<pb n="152" facs="tcp:204449:83"/> Departure: But the Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſters above named, <hi>viz: Ly<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dius</hi> and <hi>Hulſius,</hi> came too late to hear him ſpeak any thing. Howbeit a ſhort Pray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er was made for him; after which when he had abode a while with his Eyes fixed, and his hands lift up towards Heaven; One of the ſtanders by ſaid; <q>I am perſwaded this man doth already enjoy the Viſion of God; </q>where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>upon he earneſtly endeavoured to utter the Word <hi>Yea!</hi> And almoſt in the ſame moment ſweetly breathed forth his Soul, about half an hour after Nine of the Clock on Saturday morn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, being <hi>Jan.</hi> 7. After he had lived ſeventy eight years, ſix Months, and five dayes.</p>
            </div>
         </div>
         <div type="appendix">
            <pb n="153" facs="tcp:204449:83"/>
            <head>AN APPENDIX: WHEREIN <hi>A</hi> CHRISTIAN<hi>'s Triumph over Death is Illuſtrated by ſome more memorable Examples.</hi>
            </head>
            <p>§ 1. THE Jewiſh Maſters have a ſaying re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>corded in their <hi>Talm. Hieroſol.</hi> which <note n="*" place="margin">Buxt. <hi>Adag. He<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>braic.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>Buxtorf</hi> thus tranſlates: <hi>Non facienda ſunt Monumenta juſtis</hi> (ſc. <hi>de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>functis): Verba ipſorum ſunt monumenta ipſorum.</hi> That is, <hi>Monuments are not to be erected</hi>
               <pb n="154" facs="tcp:204449:84"/> 
               <hi>to the Righteous, when deceaſed; Their Words are their Monu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments:</hi> They need not the help of Art to perpetuate, or to em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>balm their Names, who have lived and dyed eminent Exam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ples of Piety and Holineſs; For they ſhall be <hi>had in everlaſting remembrance: The Memory of the</hi> 
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Pſal.</hi> 112. 6.</note> 
               <hi>juſt is bleſſed: but the Name of the wicked ſhall rot,</hi> Prov. 10. 7.</p>
            <p>As for that worthy and ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly perſon whoſe triumphant paſſage<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> thro' Death into the Joy of his Lord, we have al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ready had a Relation of; It may be queſtioned, whether his moſt fruitful and learned works while he lived, or his gracious ſpeeches and demean<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>our when he dyed, have contri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>buted moſt to the Eternizing of his Name; But it is beyond all Queſtion, that both the one and the other have raiſed unto him
<pb n="155" facs="tcp:204449:84"/> a Monument <hi>Aere perennius;</hi> and as in both he hath been an eminent Inſtrument of Glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rifying God in the World, and ſtrengthening the Faith of his Brethren; ſo his Name will be remembred with Honour, and Thankſgiving to God on the account of both, from Gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration to Generation. We have beheld in him what <hi>Bernard</hi> tells us he ſaw in dying <hi>Gerar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dus;</hi> viz. <hi>Hominem in morte ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ultantem, &amp; inſultantem morti.</hi> i. e. <hi>A man greatly rejoycing in death, and inſulting over death;</hi> which teacheth us that the Apoſtles holy Triumph, <hi>O death</hi> 
               <note place="margin">1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 15. 55.</note> 
               <hi>where is thy Sting! O Grave where is thy Victory!</hi> is no vain flouriſh of words, or empty Speculation; but a Truth ſeal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed to, in the Experience of a Chriſtian, who with a Joy un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpeakable and full of Glory,
<pb n="156" facs="tcp:204449:85"/> can joyn with him in the Ago<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nyes of Death, in his following Song of Praiſe; <hi>Thanks be to God, which giveth us the Victory, thro' our Lord Jeſus Chriſt.</hi> 
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Ver.</hi> 57.</note>
            </p>
            <p>In ſuch inſtances as theſe, we have a very valuable Evi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence of the Truth and Excel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lency of the Chriſtian Religi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, and the Certainty of a fu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture State, and bleſſed Immor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tality: Thoſe things muſt needs be real in themſelves, whoſe Efficacy is ſo great upon the Soul of a man in ſuch an hour; Death is no Fancy; neither can Fables, with what Art or Cunning ſoever they are devi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed, relieve a man againſt the bitter pangs of it: The proud boaſts of the Atheiſt and De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bauchee are ſoon quelled by this King of Terrors; the very thought of whoſe approach ſur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prizes them with Conſterna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion
<pb n="157" facs="tcp:204449:85"/> and guilty fears; But the lively hope of Pardon in the Blood of Chriſt, the Smiles of a reconciled God, and foretaſtes of heavenly Joy, make the true and ſincere Chriſtian more than a Conqueror in this Conflict: He can fear no evil becauſe God is with him, whoſe pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſence makes his Sick-bed eaſie, and gives him Proſpect of the greateſt Gain in the loſs of this Temporal Life. He can ſay as the holy 'Apoſtle, <hi>To me to live is Chriſt, to dye is Gain, Phil.</hi> 1. 21.</p>
            <p>The holy Life of the Righte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous is abundantly recommend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed to our imitation by their bleſſed Death; The advantage of whoſe End made <hi>Balaam</hi> ſay, <hi>Let me dye the Death of the Righteous and let my laſt End be like his!</hi> And certainly it is no ſmall. Honour that God hath
<pb n="158" facs="tcp:204449:86"/> put upon the Profeſſion of the Proteſtant Religion, by afford<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to many of the moſt Zea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lous Aſſertors thereof, ſuch an <hi>abundant entrance into the ever<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>laſting</hi> 
               <note place="margin">2 <hi>Pet.</hi> 1. 11.</note> 
               <hi>Kingdom of their Lord and Saviour Jeſus Chriſt;</hi> ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to whoſe pure Word they have reformed themſelves, and in whoſe Merits alone they have Truſted. Not only the conſtant and triumphant death of thouſands, who by the curſed Tyranny and Cruelty of Papiſts have been brought to Seal their Profeſſion with their Blood; but alſo the placid and moſt Chriſtian End of others that have dyed in their Beds, hath left great Convictions upon the Minds of Beholders (tho' be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore Enemies to their Religion) that there hath indeed been <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, an heavenly Excellency in it which they knew not of.
<pb n="159" facs="tcp:204449:86"/> This cauſed a Phyſitian of the Popiſh Religion, that attended upon Dr. <hi>Ames</hi> in his laſt ſick<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs at <hi>Rotterdam,</hi> when he ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerved what an extraordinary ſpirit of Faith and Holineſs breathed in him to the laſt, to expreſs himſelf after this man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner: <hi>Siccine moriuntur Refor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mati!</hi> i. e. <hi>Do Proteſtants dye at this Rate!</hi> And well indeed may they be ſurprized with wonder at ſuch Examples, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe the Principles of that Religion which they profeſs af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ford no ſuch Conſolations, or any firm ground for them, to thoſe that live and dye therein. When they come to dye, they find their Debaucheries to be more than Venial Sins, and the Guilt of them ſuch as will not be expiated by any of thoſe Means which they have truſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed to while living under the
<pb n="160" facs="tcp:204449:87"/> ſtrength of Papal deluſions; and the moſt refined and Superſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tious Devoto's in that Religion are in no better caſe, when by Death ſummoned before the dreadful Tribunal of Divine Juſtice, at whoſe Barre their own Righteouſneſs (tho' patcht up with a thouſand humane In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ventions) will ſtand them in no ſtead: To ſay nothing of thoſe Idolatries which they are taught to practiſe as the moſt effectu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>al means of meriting Heaven, and which accordingly they principally place their Confi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence in: But O how ſadly diſappointed will they be, when Death arreſts them, who have no better Antidote againſt its fatal Sting, than Popery can furniſh them with! They muſt, if their Conſciences be awa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kened, leave the World with trembling Horror, and breathe
<pb n="161" facs="tcp:204449:87"/> out their laſt with a ſad com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plaint of the wretched Cheat of that pretended Religion, which fails them in their great<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſt Extremity. Well may they then take up the dying words of * <hi>Joannes Semeca,</hi> who about <note place="margin">An Emi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nent Civi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lian in <hi>Ger<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>many.</hi>
               </note> the Year 1267. is reported to have left the World with this doleful Reflection. <q>In our Life-time we had thoſe who would frequent the Quire for us, who would till our Lands; <note place="margin">Melch. Adam.</note> who would ſay Maſs, and pray the Canonical Hours for us: But where now ſhall we find any one that will deſcend into Hell for us, and deli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver us?</q>
            </p>
            <p>§. 2. But it is time to return from this digreſſion, and to pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſecute our purpoſe, which is to preſent the Reader with ſome more eminent Inſtances of the
<pb n="162" facs="tcp:204449:88"/> Grace and Mercy of God to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards, and the Efficacy of a lively Faith in, others of his Servants in their <hi>laſt Hours;</hi> who have been zealous Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſors and Propagators of the True Religion and Faith of Chriſt while they lived, and have left this World with an holy Triumph in the full Aſſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance of Eternal Bleſſings, when they dyed. My deſign is, only to ſingle out a few Inſtances, from many that might be with equal advantage pitcht upon, were it not for ſwelling this little Tract beyond its due bounds.</p>
            <p>And the firſt I ſhall mention <note place="margin">Mr. <hi>Rol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lock.</hi>
               </note> is, that memorable Example of a Chriſtian and happy End, which ſome account of the laſt Hours of Mr. <hi>Rollock</hi> may fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſh us with, who departed this Life at <hi>Edinburgh, Feb.</hi> 8.
<pb n="163" facs="tcp:204449:88"/> 
               <hi>Anno</hi> 1598. being the Forty third year of his Age.</p>
            <p>§. 3. He was while living an eminent and very uſeful Inſtru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment in the Reformation of the Church of <hi>Scotland,</hi> which he ſought to promote by Evange<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lical Means, in the exerciſe of all Diligence in the Miniſtry of the Word, by his Learned and pious Writings, and moſt of all by a ſingular Example of Holineſs and practical Religi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on in his Life and Converſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion; which rendred him a burning and a ſhining Light in his day. Beſides his extraordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nary Labours on ſpecial Occa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſions, he had for ſome years before his death the principal Charge and Preſidency over the then newly erected Academy of <hi>Edinburgh</hi> committed to him, which he adminiſtred to the
<pb n="164" facs="tcp:204449:89"/> great advantage of thoſe under his care, and indeed of the whole Church; and in the faithful diſcharge of his duty in that great Truſt, his Lord found him when he came to call him from this evil world into his Heavenly Kingdom and Glory; and how great his Affecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on was towards the ſervice of his Lord, and what his care for the peace of <hi>Jeruſalem,</hi> and the flourſhing of true Religion, when himſelf was leaving this World, will be abundantly ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nifeſt in many paſſages during his laſt Sickneſs, which ſhall be recited in their proper place and order.</p>
            <p>When he found his diſtem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per prevail, according to his wonted Prudence he ſet in or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der what might concern his Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mily when he was gone, and prepared himſelf for a ready
<pb n="165" facs="tcp:204449:89"/> and chearful ſubmiſſion to the Will of God. And when two of his ſpecial Friends came to viſit him (that were Perſons of ſome note and Eminency) he beſought them that they would go to the King (who was then Young) and ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hort him, as from him, to abide conſtant and unmoveable in the Profeſſion of the True Religion to the end, and by no means ſuffer himſelf either by the hopes of enlarging his Kingdom, or the ſecret arts of Wicked men to be moved therefrom. The eſteem and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verence he had for the Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſters of Chriſt, he expreſt after this manner,</p>
            <p>
               <q>This Miniſtry of Chriſt, though mean and abject in the account of men, ſhall at length ſhine with illuſtrious Glory.</q>
            </p>
            <pb n="166" facs="tcp:204449:90"/>
            <p> §. 4. Afterwards the Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſters of <hi>Edenburgh</hi> came to him and when they were ſet down he addreſt himſelf to them in a copious and very ſolemn ſpeech, wherein he tells them; <q>That being worn out with his ſick<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, he breathed after and hoped for the cloſe and Period of this life: And (ſaith he) I have not ſo learned or taught Chriſt, but that in him I ſhould feel comfort under theſe Sorrows. The thred of my life will ſhortly be broken off, and I muſt paſs unto that countrey which I have long and earneſtly de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſired after.</q>
            </p>
            <p>Then he proceeds to a Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thetical recommendation of the Univerſity to their care; and makes a moſt ſolemn Proteſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion (as in the preſence of
<pb n="167" facs="tcp:204449:90"/> God, before whoſe Tribunal he muſt immediately appear) of his integrity and faithfulneſs in his Truſt, both as a Paſtor, and Rector of the Univerſity; That he had never ſuffered himſelf to be byaſſed by any corrupt or ſiniſter end, nor had any burthen upon his Conſcience with reſpect thereto: He pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſed the great care he had alwayes taken of the publick peace; but added,</p>
            <p>
               <q>Yet neither did the love of Peace ſo bewitch me, as that I ſhould not diſtinguiſh betwixt genuine and adulte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rate Peace; nor did my Affe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction towards my Prince ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duce me, ſo as that to plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure him I ſhould bring the leaſt ſpot upon my Conſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence: But the Candor of my actions will ſhine when I am dead.</q>
            </p>
            <pb n="168" facs="tcp:204449:91"/>
            <p> He exhorted them to mutu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>al peace and love; telling them<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> 
               <q>There was nothing more un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeemly than that the Preach<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers of Peace ſhould be rent with ſtrife and diſcord amon<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> themſelves; eſpecially at ſuc<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> a time when the commo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> Enemy (the Papiſt) lay i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> wait for their ruine.</q>
            </p>
            <p>And after Exhortations to render all dutiful reſpect and Obedience to their Prince; he diſmiſt them with this Benedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction.</p>
            <p>
               <q>The God and Father of Je<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſus Chriſt enrich you with all bleſſing, and ſtrengthen you with all might unto the vigorous diſcharge of your Miniſtry.</q>
            </p>
            <p>§. 5. When the Night came on, death ſeemed to be haſten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, which he perceiving, entred
<pb n="169" facs="tcp:204449:91"/> into ſuch diſcourſes of Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venly things as ſeemed to the by-ſtanders ſo much above the rate of humane capacity to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive and utter, that they were all filled with a joyful aſtoniſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ent in hearing of them.</p>
            <p>The Phyſitians came and en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deavoured (but in vain) by proper Medicines to aſſwage the force of his diſtemper; whereupon turning his ſpeech to God, he ſaid, <hi>Thou O God ſhalt heal me:</hi> And then pour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed out his prayers with a moſt ardent Zeal for the Remiſſion of his ſins through the Merit of the one and only Sacrifice of Chriſt; profeſſing that he eſteemed all things (though in appearance never ſo great) to be but dung, for the excel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lency of Chriſt Jeſus; earneſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly calling upon God that he would bring him to an happy
<pb n="170" facs="tcp:204449:92"/> and triumphant period of thi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> Life, and grant that being co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vered with the Wings of Mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy, he might ſweetly ſleep i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> the boſom of Jeſus, and enjoy that ſight of Gods face which with frequent pantings he thir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſted for.</p>
            <p>
               <q>I have ſeen thee darkly (ſaid he) in the glaſs of thy Word; O grant me the long and much deſired frui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of thy Countenance!</q>
            </p>
            <p>He diſcourſed at that rate concerning the Reſurrection, and Eternal Life, as if he had alrea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy forſaken the earth, and been tranſlated into Heaven; with ſo great ſence, and Life of Af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fection did he ſpeak of theſe things: And then taking each one by the hand that was pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent with him, like the Patri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>archs of old, he bleſſed them with words full of Gravity and
<pb n="171" facs="tcp:204449:92"/> Holineſs; cloſing his Benedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction with ſuitable Exhortati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons to every one. That Night beyond Expectation he got a little reſt.</p>
            <p>And the day following the Magiſtrates of the City, with many other perſons of quality came to viſit him: To whom he made a very grave diſcourſe, in which he earneſtly recom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mended the Univerſity to their favour and care, and nomina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted a fit perſon to them for his Succeſſor therein: And as to his private concerns, he affe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctionately recommended to them alſo his dear Wife (who was then big with Child) greatly praiſing her love and tender<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs towards him in all his weakneſs, and Afflictions; ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding,</p>
            <p>
               <q>I ingenuouſly profeſs to you, I have not laid up two Pence
<pb n="172" facs="tcp:204449:93"/> out of all my Stipends; for theſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> worldly things were not my care, nor did I ever ſet my heart upon them.</q>
            </p>
            <p>Thoſe preſent ſolemnly pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſed to anſwer his deſire, i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> all that he had mentioned t<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> them; whereupon he exhorte<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> the Profeſſors of Philoſophy t<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> perſevere in their work, an<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> yield due obedience to his Suc<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ceſſor. And then he ſaid,<q> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> thank my God, that my me<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>mory, ſight, hearing, and th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> reſt of my ſenſes are as ſtrong and lively as ever; But m<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> heart is eſtranged from thi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> world; and why, O Lord Jeſu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> ſhouldſt not thou enjoy m<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> Heart, who only haſt a righ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> thereto? This hath been my endeavour all my Life long, to dedicate and conſecrate my heart to thee; take it to th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> ſelf, I beſeech thee, that i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <pb n="173" facs="tcp:204449:93"/> may remain with thee.</q>
            </p>
            <p>§. 6. After he had ſpoken <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>heſe things, a gentle ſleep came upon him, out of which when he awaked, he expreſt a moſt ardent breathing to be diſſol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved, and to be with Chriſt.</p>
            <p>
               <q>Come Lord Jeſus (ſaid he) break off the thred of this miſerable Life! Make haſt, O Lord, Tarry not! Jeſus hath Redeemed me, that he might grant to me (not this frail, but) eternal Life. Come Jeſus! Grant me that life for which thou haſt redeemed me!</q>
            </p>
            <p>And when thoſe that ſtood about him lamented the great loſs they ſhould have of him, he ſaid;</p>
            <p>
               <q>I have paſs'd through all the Steps of this life; and am now come to the laſt,
<pb n="174" facs="tcp:204449:94"/> why ſhould I go back again? By the aid of thy preſence, O Lord Jeſus, I ſhall happi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly meaſure this Step alſo: Lead thou me into that Glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry which I have only ſeen through a Glaſs: O that I were converſant with thee!</q>
            </p>
            <p>Upon occaſion of ſome one ſignifying to him, that the next day was the Sabbath day, he thus expreſt himſelf.</p>
            <p>
               <q>Let thy Sabbath, O Lord, begin mine eternal Sabbath: Let my Eternal Sabbath re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive the pledge of an hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>py beginning from thy Sab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bath.</q>
            </p>
            <p>Towards the middle of the Night he got a little reſt, which the ſtrength of his diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eaſe ſoon interrupted; and he ſuppoſing his laſt hour to draw near, ſent for Mr. <hi>Walter Bal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>canquel,</hi> unto whom, when he
<pb n="175" facs="tcp:204449:94"/> was come in, he thus addreſſed himſelf:</p>
            <p>
               <q>Foraſmuch as you have for a long time had a Paſtoral charge at <hi>Edinburgh,</hi> and our friendſhip is of no late date, I took care to have you ſent for, that I might make manifeſt unto all the Reverence which from my Cradle I have had for the Miniſtry of Chriſt: I have indeed, according to the meaſure of my gift, al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ready poured out my Pray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers into the boſom of God; and now I intreat you to pray for me, I will joyn with my Heart and Affection; only deſire not the protracting of this Life.</q>
            </p>
            <p>Whereupon all that were preſent, falling on their Knees, Mr. <hi>Balcanquel</hi> prayed; but a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mong other things he earneſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly deſired that it might pleaſe
<pb n="176" facs="tcp:204449:95"/> God to ſpare ſo worthy a man with them for ſome longer time, ſeeing both the Church and Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon-wealth had ſo great need of his ſervice; whereupon Mr. <hi>Rol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lock</hi> interrupted him, ſaying,</p>
            <p>
               <q>I have enough of this Life; the only thing I deſire is that heavenly Life, which is hid with God in Chriſt.</q>
            </p>
            <p>When prayer was ended, he brake forth into an earneſt com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mendation of the Efficacy of the Word Preached.</p>
            <p>
               <q>The Word (ſaid he) is both Life, and Death: nor can any <note place="margin">2 Cor. 2. 16.</note> be ſaved without the Word. Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieve me! 'Tis no trifling mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter to preach the Word: It is not like the interpreting a Text of <hi>Plato</hi> or <hi>Ariſtotle;</hi> or the ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king an Oration embelliſhed with the alluring Ornaments of ſpeech: The Preaching of the Word conſiſts in Holineſs, Hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mility,
<pb n="177" facs="tcp:204449:95"/> and the powerful de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monſtration of the Spirit: How great my eſteem of it hath ever been, God is Witneſs!</q>
            </p>
            <p>Then turning his diſcourſe into Prayer, he ſaid; <q>Come Lord Jeſus! break aſunder the Nerves of theſe Eyes, and give me other Eyes! I de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſire to be diſſolved, and to be with thee; Haſten thy coming, O Lord Jeſus, and deferre no longer! Let this faint life go forth, that the better Life of God may enter in: Lord Jeſus put forth thy hand into this body, and take out this Soul unto thy ſelf.</q>
            </p>
            <p>§. 7. From that time till the Sabbath day morning he kept ſilence, when again the long<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ings he had after his Fathers Houſe, were breathed forth in theſe words.</p>
            <pb n="178" facs="tcp:204449:96"/>
            <p>
               <q>Come Lord, and tarry not, I am wearyed with the loathing of day and night; Come Lord Jeſus, that I may come to thee! O ſweet and happy divorce from this Life: Come Lord, who art my ſweet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, and ſet this Soul at li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>berty that it may enjoy thee it's Husband; break this Heart of mine in two, that it may fly to thee it's Head.</q>
            </p>
            <p>To this one replyed, Hither<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to Chriſt hath poſſeſſed your whole heart, and he will take it whole unto himſelf. To which he returned anſwer,</p>
            <p>
               <q>I deſire the breaking in two of this Heart, that this natural Life may be let out, and it may be wholly re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pleniſht with the Life of Chriſt.</q>
            </p>
            <p>Then one of the by-ſtanders ſaid; Let no anxiety trouble
<pb n="179" facs="tcp:204449:96"/> you; your Lord is now haſten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing.</p>
            <p>
               <q>Thoſe (ſaid he) are wel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come tidings unto me; I would my Funeral was to be to morrow.</q>
            </p>
            <p>Another ſaid, Happy is that Soul which is ſo near to the Lord as yours is. To which he replyed,</p>
            <p>
               <q>There is nothing in me which I account not as dung, that I may win Chriſt: Chriſt is the only matter of my Comfort; my own Righte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſneſs is a menſtruous cloth.</q>
            </p>
            <p>Being asked, if he deſired to ſpeak with any of the Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſters; he ſaid, he would not give them trouble now they were juſt preparing themſelves to preach.</p>
            <p>
               <q>Let me (ſaid he) chatter with my Lord like a Crane.</q> Being informed that Sermon
<pb n="180" facs="tcp:204449:97"/> was begun. <q>Lord (ſaid he) grant that I may ſee what others now hear!</q>
            </p>
            <p>About noon, when one com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forted him with the remem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brance of his unwearied pains and diligent endeavour to pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mote the Glory of God all his life time; he replyed,</p>
            <p>
               <q>I have nothing to Glory in but the Mercy of God in Chriſt Jeſus: All other things I count but loſs!</q>
            </p>
            <p>After a little reſt, a perſon of conſiderable rank viſiting him, he again took the occa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion of an earneſt recommen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dation of what might tend to the promoting of Religion to his care in his Station: And in the following Night he was obſerved to ſay; <q>I have a peaceful mind in a ſick bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy; I am not perplex't with the fear of Death, Sin, or Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tan,
<pb n="181" facs="tcp:204449:97"/> they have no Dominion over me: yet ſo great is the weight of my diſtemper, that it is much beyond expecta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion that I ſubſiſt to this hour. He bruiſes me as with a Peſtle in the Mortar of Affliction, that he may form me for his own Kingdom.</q>
            </p>
            <p>§. 8. On the next day being Monday, he ſaid to thoſe about him,</p>
            <p>
               <q>It may ſeem ſtrange, ſee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing I am ſo ſorely handled with my diſeaſe, that my life ſhould be protracted thus long: But with patience I wait for the good pleaſure of the Lord: Let him do with me what pleaſeth him, I will not diſpute it with him: What is man that he ſhould dare to contend with God! yea though he ſhould thruſt
<pb n="182" facs="tcp:204449:98"/> him down to Hell, he muſt obey, and not reply upon God: Be gracious unto me, O Lord, for Chriſt Jeſus ſake: I am not aſhamed to profeſs that I never before attained to ſo high a pitch of the Knowledge of God, as I have done in this ſickneſs. O what a fearful thing is it to fall into the hands of the Lord! But Mercy is laid up for me in Chriſt. Why art thou Sor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rowful, O my Soul? why art thou caſt down within me? thou ſhalt by and by obtain a moſt pleaſant ſight, and congreſs.</q>
            </p>
            <p>Towards evening, he told his Friends that he experienced in himſelf the truth of the ſixth Pſalm, and repeated ſome Paſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſages therein; as <hi>verſe</hi> 2. <hi>Have mercy upon me, O Lord, for I am weak: O Lord heal me, for</hi>
               <pb n="183" facs="tcp:204449:98"/> 
               <hi>my bones are vexed:</hi> To which he added, <q>Chriſt will bear my burthen, and I will fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low, him being unheld by his Grace.</q>
            </p>
            <p>When thoſe that were about him, obſerving the bitterneſs and extremity of his diſeaſe, brake out into Tears and Lamentati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on for him.</p>
            <p>
               <q>Lament not my caſe (ſaid he) but weep for your own ſins; ſeeing none are free from ſin, none want occaſion of weeping; but as for me, I ſhall quickly ſee the end and conſummation of all.</q>
            </p>
            <p>The care of his Funeral he recommended to two of his intire Friends preſent, and when he had finiſhed his Directions about what he would have done therein; he ſaid,</p>
            <p>
               <q>Why ſhould I not take care of this body, ſeeing that
<pb n="184" facs="tcp:204449:99"/> alſo ſhall be glorified, and made conformable to the glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rious body of Chriſt: (and looking upon his hands) <hi>Theſe very hands ſhall ſhine with ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cellent Glory.</hi>
               </q>
            </p>
            <p>After this he was not able to ſpeak much; but to the ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry laſt what he did utter was with a wonderful ſavour, ſtill expreſſing the inward joy and peace of his Soul, and a moſt aſſured Confidence of a com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pleat and glorious Victory in this laſt conflict; and in a few hours he finiſhed his courſe; and ſweetly ſlept in Jeſus.</p>
            <p>Before I paſs to another Sto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry, I cannot but mention one thing more that happened a little before this holy man drew his laſt breath; And it is this.</p>
            <p>One of his kindred coming in to ſee him, and perceiving that he was nigh to death,
<pb n="185" facs="tcp:204449:99"/> being himſelf a Stranger to Religion and Piety, yet convin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ced that it could not but be well with ſo holy a man as Mr. <hi>Rollock,</hi> entreated of him, That when he came to Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven, he would Mediate for him and the reſt of his Friends here below. But how grievous this ignorant and impious requeſt was to the Soul of this bleſſed Saint, will be eaſily gueſſed by thoſe, that as he did, love the honour of Chriſt more than their own lives; Though be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore he lay as one ready to give up the Ghoſt, at the hear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of this, his Zeal was ſo ſtirred in him, that he raiſes himſelf upright, and with a great fervency replyes, <q> I re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fuſe that Office: Chriſt is the only Mediator. </q>And ſo deep was the impreſſion of trou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble this made upon his Spirit,
<pb n="186" facs="tcp:204449:100"/> that a while after, when his elder Brother came to viſit him, he left this charge upon him.</p>
            <p>
               <q>Do you (ſaid he) rebuke that Kinſman of ours, and ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moniſh him that he take ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther courſe, otherwiſe there is no Salvation for him, but moſt certain ruine.</q>
            </p>
            <p>§. 9. The next inſtance I ſhall touch upon, is that of Mr. <hi>John</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Oecolampa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dius.</note> 
               <hi>Oecolampadius,</hi> who while he lived was alſo an eminent Inſtrument in the Reformation of Religion, and one of the firſt (with <hi>Zuinglius</hi> and others) whoſe labours it pleaſed God to ſucceed for the accompliſhing of an happy beginning of that great work in <hi>Baſil,</hi> and other of the <hi>Sviſſe Cantons:</hi> He was a perſon very conſiderable both for his Learning and Piety; but
<pb n="187" facs="tcp:204449:100"/> for nothing more to be com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mended, than for his Peaceable temper, and Chriſtian Modera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, in thoſe controverſies with which the reformed Churches were then exerciſed among themſelves in the buſineſs of the <hi>Lords Supper:</hi> For though he was both free in declaring, and conſtant in aſſerting that truth which the Lord had made known to him, yet his great care was, <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, <hi>to ſpeak the truth in love;</hi> and to ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nage the defence thereof with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out bitterneſs towards, or Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vocation of, thoſe that did in that point diſſent from him. And as he was a man ſtudious of Peace in his life, ſo it plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed the Lord to guard his Soul with a Peace that paſſeth all underſtanding, and to fill his Heart with Spiritual and Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venly joy when he came to dye.</p>
            <pb n="188" facs="tcp:204449:101"/>
            <p> After he had for ſome con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiderable time laboured in the Miniſtry of the Word at <hi>Baſil,</hi> it pleaſed God there to viſit him with his laſt ſickneſs, in the Forty ninth year of his Age, which he preſently ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prehended would prove mortal to him, and accordingly gave warning to his Friends that they ſhould expect no other: But ſo far was he from being terrifyed by the approach of death, that on the contrary he expreſt the greateſt longings after that Heavenly light, and Crown of Glory which he ſaw ready prepared for him, ſo ſoon as the earthly houſe of this Ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bernacle ſhould be taken down: He waited not for the Conſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lations of others in this laſt con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>flict, but was ready to Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter Conſolation to all that were about him; inſomuch that
<pb n="189" facs="tcp:204449:101"/> his moſt Chriſtian and comfor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>table End, was no leſs for the Confirmation and encourage<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of the Godly in their Holy profeſſion, than his Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine and blameleſs Life had been. He was an example of dying well, as he had been before of living well: of which abundant teſtimony is given by thoſe worthy men that familiarly and almoſt conſtantly converſed. with him in theſe his laſt hours. Among whom <hi>Simon Grynaeus,</hi> a man whoſe praiſe is in the Reformed Churches, was one; who hath left us the ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>count of the following diſcourſe that this pious Servant of Chriſt made to him and the reſt of the Miniſters of the Church, a little before his departure; which alone is ſufficient to ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtifie all that hath been before ſaid of the frame of his Spirit
<pb n="190" facs="tcp:204449:102"/> upon his dying bed. It is as follows.</p>
            <p>§. 10. <q>You ſee Brethren what the buſineſs is: The Lord is at hand, he cometh, and is now about to take me hence: and therefore I was deſirous to call you firſt, and with my deareſt Friends to ſati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ate this Soul of mine with a ſincere Joy in the Lord, and true conſolation. What ſhall we ſay then in this laſt Embrace, O ye Servants of Chriſt, whom the ſame Love to their Lord, the ſame Stu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy, and the ſame Doctrine hath moſt cloſely knit toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther! Salvation is obtained; It is obtained (I ſay) by Chriſt; and we have all Confidence of the Kingdom of God: Our Doctrine is certain, and light is prepared for our feet: It
<pb n="191" facs="tcp:204449:102"/> is meet that all Sorrow, all fears of Life or Death, all doubting and error ſhould be baniſht far away: Only this (my Brethren!) this only remains, that we conſtantly and faithfully perſevere in thoſe footſteps of Chriſt which we have already entred up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, by maintaining Purity of Doctrine in the firſt place, and then by a Life in all things conformed to the true Word of God: Other things he will take care of who is Mighty, and of his own ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cord watcheth his own, even Chriſt our Lord: He will de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fend his own Church: Let us ſee to it therefore (Bre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thren!) that our light ſo ſhine that God the Father may be glorified in us, and the Name of Chriſt rendred illuſtrious through the light of your
<pb n="192" facs="tcp:204449:103"/> Sincerity and holy Life. See that you love one another in Truth; and lead your whole Life as under the Eye, and in the ſight of God: 'Tis to no purpoſe to preſs Piety with words only; The light of Truth and Holineſs in Life, with the true and Heavenly Spirit of the Mind, are ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſary, if we would vanquiſh Satan, and convert the World to our Lord Chriſt. For (O my Brethren!) What clouds are there ariſing, and what a tempeſt draws near! what alienation of men, and what impiety is at the door! But Brethren! It behoves you to ſtand faſt, and to abide it: The Lord himſelf will be pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent with you in his Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerns: O that my Lot were to undergo theſe dangers with you! and that I could often
<pb n="193" facs="tcp:204449:103"/> ſpill this Life for the Truth! But however Love is undivi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded, and the bond in Chriſt indiſſoluble; all things are common to the Godly among themſelves.</q>
            </p>
            <p>Theſe things he uttered with reſpect to the common Cauſe of Religion; And as to what concern'd himſelf he told them,</p>
            <p>
               <q>I matter not the ſcandal which ſome have imputed to me, as if I had corrupted the Truth: Through the Grace of God, I am now going to the Tribunal of Chriſt with a good Conſcience: There it will be manifeſt that the Church hath not been ſeduced by us. And of this Solemn Proteſtation I leave you my Witneſſes, which I alſo con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firm with my laſt breath.</q>
            </p>
            <p>The next day (which was the fifteenth from his firſt ſick<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs)
<pb n="194" facs="tcp:204449:104"/> he cauſed his Children to be brought before him, and firſt took them by the hand, then ſtroaked each of them, and calling them by their Names ſaid,</p>
            <p>
               <q>Thou <hi>Euſebius,</hi> thou <hi>Irene,</hi> and thou <hi>Alethea,</hi> my dear Children! ſee that you love God.</q>
            </p>
            <p>And becauſe by reaſon of their age, they were not yet ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pable of attending to the Charge of their dying Father (the Eldeſt being but about three years Old) he turned him to his Wife and the reſt of his Relations preſent, and ſaid,</p>
            <p>
               <q>It is you that I have bound by this charge to do your Endeavour, that according to my deſire and what they now hear, my Children may be Pious, Peaceable, and Faith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful. </q> This he ſpake with al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>luſion
<pb n="195" facs="tcp:204449:104"/> to the ſignification of their Names: And their Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther with the reſt, ſignifing their acceptance of this charge; he deſired them to take a way the Children again.</p>
            <p>The Laſt night he lived here being come, his inward Joy did no way abate, but rather increaſe as death drew nearer to him. One of his intimate friends coming, in he asked him, <hi>what News he had brought;</hi> his Friend told him, <hi>None: Why then</hi> (ſaid he) <hi>I will tell you news; I ſhall in a little time be with the Lord Chriſt.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>A while after, when they asked, <hi>If the light did not of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fend him;</hi> touching his breaſt, he ſaid, <hi>Abundé lucis eſt! Here is abundance of Light!</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The next morning his fatal hour came on, before which, he prayed with an ardent Affecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on
<pb n="196" facs="tcp:204449:105"/> for the Remiſſion of Sin, repeating the 51 <hi>Pſalm,</hi> from the beginning to the end; And then after a little pauſe and breathing, he renewed his pray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er in theſe words: <hi>Chriſt Jeſus ſave me!</hi> which were the laſt he uttered, and then ſweetly breathed forth his pious Soul into the boſom of his Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deemer. He changed this Life for an Heavenly, on the firſt day of <hi>December</hi> in the year 1531. And as Mr. <hi>Rollock</hi> pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſed upon his death-bed, that he had laid up nothing of this World in his Life; ſo it is ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerved of this good man, <q>That he made no Will, becauſe he had nothing to diſpoſe of:</q>
            </p>
            <p>So far were theſe firſt Reform<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers from ſeeking great things for themſelves! <hi>Riches profit not in the day of wrath, but Righte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſneſs delivereth from death:</hi> 
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Pro.</hi> 11. 4.</note>
               <pb n="197" facs="tcp:204449:105"/> 
               <hi>To be rich towards God,</hi> to have <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Luk.</hi> 12. 21</note> an Heart filled with Grace and Spiritual Comfort, and <hi>the te<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtimony</hi> 
               <note place="margin">2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 1. 12</note> 
               <hi>of a good Conſcience, that with ſimplicity and godly ſincerity we have had our converſation in the World;</hi> will prove the beſt portion when we come to dye; and afford ſuch eaſe to us up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on a ſick bed, as all the Trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure under Heaven cannot pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cure the like.</p>
            <p>§. 11. The Jewiſh Writers, from that Paſſage of the <hi>Pſal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſt:</hi> 
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Pſa.</hi> 41. 3.</note> 
               <hi>The Lord will ſtrengthen him upon the bed of languiſhing; thou wilt make all his bed in his ſickneſs;</hi> have a Proverbial ſaying <hi>in Tract. Nedar:</hi> to this ſence; <hi>Majeſtas divina ſedet ad caput lecti aegrotantis: i. e. The divine Majeſty ſitteth (or abi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deth) at the ſick mans beds<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>head.</hi> His ſick bed is turned
<pb n="198" facs="tcp:204449:106"/> into a Sanctuary, by the Gra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cious preſence of God with him. This we have ſeen veri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fied in the former Examples, and ſhall yet meet with a fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther Confirmation of, in the experience of <hi>Joachimus Curaeus,</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Curaeus.</note> a Learned and Pious Doctor of Phyſick in <hi>Germany;</hi> and a Zealous Proteſtant; who fini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhed his courſe in the year 1573. being the Forty firſt currant of his age. He was a perſon that eſteemed Religi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on to be his greateſt concern while he lived, and continual<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly exerciſed himſelf in a dili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gent and ſerious practice there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of; And as he would by no means be diverted from work<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing out his own Salvation with fear and trembling, by fervent Prayer, and all manner of Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly Converſation in the World, ſo it pleaſed God when he cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led
<pb n="199" facs="tcp:204449:106"/> him out of the World, to afford him ſuch an abundant Enjoyment and ſence of his love in Chriſt, as carryed him through the Agonies of death with a more than ordinary Triumph and rejoycing. In his laſt hours it was moſt con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vincingly manifeſt, that Chriſt had given unto him a large draught of that water of Life, which was in him a well of water ſpringing up unto Eter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nal Life; from which bleſſed Fountain he poured forth abun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dant Conſolations to all that were with him in that Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>flict, if ſo happy a departure, and ſo ſweet a ſleep, as death was made to him, may yet be called a Conflict.</p>
            <p>When he found his ſickneſs had prevailed over Nature ſo far, as that his diſſolution muſt needs be haſtning on, he whol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly
<pb n="200" facs="tcp:204449:107"/> applyed himſelf to ardent Prayers and Supplications unto God, making uſe of that exer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciſe for the eaſe and ſupport of his Soul in ſickneſs, which had been his delight and Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fort in his health; And ſeveral times in one day, cauſing his his Wife and Children to come to him, he did with an inex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſible Zeal and Affection ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hort them to Piety and Virtue; and then in a ſolemn manner recommended both them and his laſt charge to them, to the bleſſing of God; who in this alſo heard the Prayers of his Servant; and raiſed up two of his Sons after him, to be emi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nent examples both of Piety Virtue and Learning in their Generation; thereby making good his word, That <hi>the Gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration of the upright ſhall be bleſſed.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb n="201" facs="tcp:204449:107"/>
            <p> §. 12. Being taken away in the midſt of his years, at that age which was the ripeſt for Service, he would often repeat the mournful complaint of <hi>He<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zekiah; I have cut off like a Weaver my life,</hi> &amp;c: But then his perfect acquieſcence in the will of God, and rejoycing in his Salvation, was as frequent<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly expreſt, in the following words, which are ſome of thoſe holy ſayings which plentifully iſſued from his pure Heart in this laſt ſickneſs: <hi>viz.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <q>I am broken, O Lord! but it ſatisfies me that thy hand hath done this, not the De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vil. The Body indeed ſuffers becauſe of Sin, but thou Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forteſt my Soul with a moſt ſure Hope, and expectation of eternal Life. I believe, O Lord! I believe; but do thou
<pb n="202" facs="tcp:204449:108"/> help mine unbelief: I have re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceived a Meſſage of death, but I will wreſtle with thee O Lord Jeſus, after the Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ample of thy holy Pilgrim <hi>Jacob,</hi> untill the Morning beams of thy light break up, ariſe, and ſhine upon me; nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther will I let thee go unleſs thou bleſs me, and my Soul be ſaved; Therefore O Jeſus Chriſt, thou wilt bleſs me, and ſave my Soul, giving un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to me a Believer, Remiſſion of Sins, Righteouſneſs and Life! Come Lord Jeſus, and let all that love thee ſay, Come! And he that loves thee not, let him be <hi>Anathema Maranatha:</hi> Thou knoweſt, O Lord, who art the ſearcher of Hearts, That I love thee; And thou loveſt me, yea thou loveſt me in Truth, and art my Redeemer by thy
<pb n="203" facs="tcp:204449:108"/> Merit and Efficacy. Into thy hands, O Lord, I com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mend my Spirit, for thou haſt Redeemed me, O Lord God of Truth.</q>
            </p>
            <p>And then reflecting upon the time of his ſickneſs, (for he dyed <hi>January</hi> 21.) he pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceeded in further expreſſions of his aſſured Confidence in God, and inward Joy, through the lively hope and foretaſt of the bleſſings of that Kingdom he was going to, after this manner:</p>
            <p>
               <q>I ſhall be with thee in the beginning of this new Year; I ſhall be ſatiated with the ſight of thee, O Lord! I ſhall drink with thee at thy Ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble the New Juice of Eter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nal Joy, even in thy Fathers houſe, where there are many Manſions; <hi>there is a place for me alſo;</hi> and there ſhall I
<pb n="204" facs="tcp:204449:109"/> ſit at thy Table. Refreſh me, O Son of God, with thy Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit, and with thy quickening preſence. I come unto thee, Jeſus Chriſt; Receive thou me according to thy Promiſe, which is the only repaſt, and Recreation of my Soul. <hi>Iam meum pectus ardet conſpectu vitae eternae, cujus verè ſentio in me initia.</hi> i. e. Now doth my Heart burn, through the ſight of Eternal Life, the Begin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nings of which I truly feel in my ſelf: And this is Life Eternal, to know thee the true God, and Jeſus Chriſt whom thou haſt ſent. Through thy goodneſs I have learned, and I have taught others, rightly to acknowledge thee: Do thou again acknowledge me, O Son of God, and em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brace me with thy Saving Grace, even with thy Holy
<pb n="205" facs="tcp:204449:109"/> Spirit; do thou preſent this Soul to thy Eternal Father, who will readily receive it from thy hand; My deſire and rejoycing is to come un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to him; and becauſe I am not yet come, all delay ſeems long unto me; O thou Sun of Righteouſneſs, light me into Eternal light and Righ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teouſneſs: I deſire, with thine Apoſtle, to be diſſolved, and to be with thee; Looſe me, that I may be with thee: I am greatly wearyed, and I wait for the entertainment which thou haſt ſhewn me. As the Traveller in his Jour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ney, at Night time deſires the Sun-riſing; ſo do I deſire after the clear light, even the ſight of the Father, Son, and Holy Ghoſt. When my voice and ſpeech ſhall fail me, Grant, O Merciful Saviour, that thy
<pb n="206" facs="tcp:204449:110"/> Holy Spirit may ſpeak unto thee in my Heart, and make interceſſion for me with groan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ings that cannot be uttered: Let his motions ſpring up in my breaſt, and move thy Heart unto Mercy towards me. Lord Jeſus Chriſt, who ſitteſt at the right hand of thy Eternal Father, receive my Spirit.</q>
            </p>
            <p>§. 13. Theſe were the Medi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tations, and this the exerciſe of this Holy man upon his dy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing bed: He felt this Taberna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cle to be falling, but knew he had an houſe not made with hands, Eternal in the Heavens; and his pious Soul was filled with Heavenly triumph, in the certain expectation of a Glori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous Reſurrection of that ſame body of his, which was now ready to be ſown in corrupti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on,
<pb n="207" facs="tcp:204449:110"/> which with an admirable ſweetneſs and comfort, he thus expreſs'd: </p>
            <q>
               <p> I ſhall ſee thee my Saviour, in my fleſh, which thou haſt exalted to the right hand of the Eternal Father; and I will give thee thanks in the preſence of thy Father, for all the Good things which thou haſt communicated un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to me. Yea thou wilt place thy Holy Angels to be the Guardians of my Body, that they may keep my duſt, which hath been, and to all Eter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nity ſhall be, the dwelling place of thy Holy Spirit. It is impoſſible that this fleſh of mine, which is the Tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple of the Holy Ghoſt, this Maſs of my body, which is quickened by the effuſion, and communication of the Spirit of Chriſt, and ſo inſerted in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the fleſh of Chriſt, ſhould
<pb n="208" facs="tcp:204449:111"/> be reduced unto nothing, or abide in death, and ever re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>main duſt and aſhes: But thou who art the Author of Life, will remand from the Earth this thine own Image, even out of the ſmalleſt Crums of duſt and aſhes that are there; By ſending forth thy breath thou wilt again build up my body alive and Glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rious, which ſhall be the ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bitation of the whole Divini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, dwelling therein to all Eternity. There ſhall we fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low the Lamb whitherſoever he ſhall go; O Guide truly fair and Divine! There ſhall we ſing a New Song: Let us rejoyce! <hi>Hallelujah!</hi>
               </p>
               <p>O Come, let us go forth to meet our Saviour: Our <note place="margin">
                     <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>
                  </note> Right as Citizens is in Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven; but in this Life we muſt begin Eternal Life, and
<pb n="209" facs="tcp:204449:111"/> follow the order which Chriſt hath appointed; We ſhall be cloathed upon, if ſo be that we be not found Naked: That moſt lovely Lamb of God which takes away the ſins of the world, will lead us unto the Fountains of living Waters, and wipe away all Tears from our Eyes. <hi>Eye hath not ſeen, nor Ear heard, neither have entred into the Heart of man, the things which God hath prepared for them that love him.</hi> This Earthly Life is Death, but that Life which Chriſt begins in me, is Life indeed; Now it is no more I that live, but Chriſt that liveth in me; therefore let him be praiſed. O hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>py Soul, in which thou Jeſus Chriſt ſitteſt as the Guide and Rector of all its actions and Motions. I ſee Heaven
<pb n="210" facs="tcp:204449:112"/> open unto me! Now letteſt thou thy Servant depart in Peace, O Lord, for mine Eyes indeed have ſeen thy Salva<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion! Thou, O Chriſt, art the Reſurrection and Life; How amiable are thy Tabernacles, O Lord! O Chriſt my Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deemer, carefully watch my Soul, that it ſuffer no detri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment by the horrible and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fernal Dragon, the Devil. Let my Soul be bound up in the bundle of Life; and let this my paſſage hence be happy; let it be to me the way to thoſe that live an immortal and Heavenly Life.</p>
            </q>
            <p>§. 14. After, this he again moſt affectionately prayed for his Wife and Children, but in terms arguing ſuch a nearneſs to God and Holy Familiarity with him, as if a man had
<pb n="211" facs="tcp:204449:112"/> been ſpeaking to his Friend, and devolving a care upon him that he knew moſt aſſuredly he would willingly take upon himſelf and ſee to; He migh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tily Comforted himſelf with the thoughts of Chriſts ſympa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thy and compaſſion, who (ſaith he) will certainly hear me in all theſe things. And when one exhorted him to be of good hope, for God would help him; he anſwered,</p>
            <p>
               <q>'Tis right: The Lord will certainly help me, by a fi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nal deliverance; according to that; <hi>Bleſſed are the dead which dye in the Lord:</hi> In the Lord then do I dye, who is my Life; I dye in the acknow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledgment, Faith, and Confi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence of Chriſt the Media<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tor, who is my Shade of defence, and my Brother, who cloatheth me with the
<pb n="212" facs="tcp:204449:113"/> garment of his Righteouſneſs; I ſhall therefore be happy, I ſhall be Righteous; O ſweet Bleſſedneſs! ſweet Righteouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs! O ſweet change and Tranſlation from Sin to In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nocency, from Darkneſs in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to Light, from Death to Life.</q>
            </p>
            <p>Many Prayers alſo he put up for the Church of God, eſpecially that the pure Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine of the Goſpel might be tranſmitted without corruption to Poſterity; and with Tears bewailed the wickedneſs of thoſe who by their corrupt Notions were an hindrance to its courſe. And once more (a little before his Soul departed) his Friends being about him, he ſolemnly recommends himſelf to Chriſt, and repeats the Confeſſion of his Faith; expreſſing great thank<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fulneſs to God for the Refor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mation,
<pb n="213" facs="tcp:204449:113"/> and for thoſe that he had uſed as Inſtruments there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in.</p>
            <p>
               <q>I am now dying (ſaid he) and diſmiſt as that Servant of God holy <hi>Simeon;</hi> I alſo being the Servant of God, and Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly; I dye in the Confeſſion of the writings of the Prophets and Holy Apoſtles; and of the Ancient Creeds; and alſo adhering to the <hi>Auguſtane Confeſſion;</hi> I give thanks to God, That of his Infinite goodneſs he hath diſpell'd the darkneſs, and reſtored to us the Light and Purity of his Goſpel.</q>
            </p>
            <p>At length, in the midſt of his Prayers and earneſt breath<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ings after God, he yielded up his Soul into the hands and boſom of his Redeemer, where he reſts from his Labours, and his works follow him.</p>
            <pb n="214" facs="tcp:204449:114"/>
            <p> §. 15. Another Inſtance wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thy of our Remembrance and imitation, I ſhall give you, in Mr. <hi>Matthew Weſenbeck,</hi> an eminent <hi>Civilian;</hi> who after he had run the courſe of an Holy Life, from his firſt Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſion to the fifty fifth year of his Age, departed this Life at <hi>Wittenburg,</hi> in the year 1586.</p>
            <p>The means by which God firſt awakened him to ſeek af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter and embrace the knowledge of the Truth, was this.</p>
            <p>While he was ſtudying the Law at <hi>Lovane,</hi> it fell out that there was a poor man in the City, who being blind made it his buſineſs to viſit the Sick, and to inſtruct and comfort them as he could with Texts of Scripture, (in which he was well verſed;) in recompence of which pious office, thoſe that
<pb n="215" facs="tcp:204449:114"/> were well diſpoſed, would re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieve his Neceſſity with a piece of Bread and Cheeſe: After ſome time, this poor man was accuſed of Hereſie, and commit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted to Priſon; near this priſon, <hi>Weſenbeck</hi> with his fellow Stu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dents were wont to recreate themſelves with the Ball; on which occaſion they often heard this blind man with a clear voice ſinging the Pſalms of <hi>David</hi> according to <hi>Luthers</hi> Metaphraſe; and this Holy ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>erciſe the good man performed with ſo much Devotion and Affection, as wrought in them a more than ordinary attention to him, although it was not without ſome danger to them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves; And it pleaſed God ſo to work upon <hi>Weſenbeck,</hi> by this example of Chriſtian con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtancy and Zeal, together with the matter which he heard,
<pb n="216" facs="tcp:204449:115"/> that thenceforward he began diligently to ſearch the Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures, and alſo to read the Wri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tings of thoſe of the Refor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med Religion; by which means he became not only fully con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vinced of the Truth, but alſo received it in the Love thereof, and abode moſt conſtant in the Faith and Practice of it to his dying day; being an eminent example of Zeal and ſtrict Pie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty in his whole life: He had an extraordinary Affection to the Holy Scriptures, but eſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cially the book of Pſalms and the New Teſtament were moſt dear and delightful to him: And notwithſtanding the neceſſary courſe of his Studyes, and (for ſome time alſo) great Practice in the Law, he uſually ſpent at fit ſeaſons no leſs than five hours in a day in Prayers and reti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red communion with God; He
<pb n="217" facs="tcp:204449:115"/> was not like many that can <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>d no leiſure for Religion, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>hat is, cannot attend to work <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ut their own Salvation: but made Conſcience to ſteer his whole courſe as a man reſol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ed for Heaven: And his Righ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>eouſneſs and Charity towards men was not inferior to his Piety towards God; He ever <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>bhorr'd thoſe Artifices which <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>re too common with practiti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>oners in the Law; his Candor, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>aithfulneſs, and Juſtice in his practice, made his Name pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cious to all that knew him; And as it pleaſed God to bleſs him with a plentiful Supply of the good things of this world, ſo Religion taught him not to <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ruſt in uncertain Riches, but <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>o be rich in good works; His way was to give a charge <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>o all his Servants, that they ſhould never turn away the
<pb n="218" facs="tcp:204449:116"/> Poor from his door without relief; And when they ha<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> not preſently regarded the poor nor liſtened ſo ſoon as they ought to their cry, himſelf would open his Window and throw down Money to them.</p>
            <p>Thus did this good man ſpend his Life and his Subſtance in the Fear of God, and work<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing Righteouſneſs; and accord<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ingly his latter end was Peace; for when he lay upon his death Bed he was filled with the Conſolations of God: He woul<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> often repeat that of the Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtle <hi>Paul,</hi> Rom. 7. <hi>O wretche<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> man that I am, who ſhall deliver me from the Body of this death! I thank God through Jeſus Chriſt our Lord.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And that; 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 1. <hi>He hath ſealed us, and given the earneſt of his Spirit in our Hearts, by which we cry, Abba, Father.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb n="219" facs="tcp:204449:116"/>
            <p> Another time with great re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>oycing he told thoſe that were with him,</p>
            <p>
               <q>That now God had ſhewn to him a place of Eternal Joy, unto which he ſhould immediately come; and the only thing he deſired, was that his coming thither might be haſtened.</q>
            </p>
            <p>He would often rehearſe di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vers paſſages out of the Pſalms; as, <hi>The Lord is nigh to all that call upon him in Truth: He will fulfill the deſire of them that fear him, he will hear their pray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er and ſave them.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And immediately before he gave up the Ghoſt, he profeſſed; <hi>That he was in Covenant with the Lord Jeſus Chriſt:</hi> which words were his laſt.</p>
            <p>§. 16. In theſe experiences we ſee that they which believe
<pb n="220" facs="tcp:204449:117"/> in Chriſt, never dye; <hi>i. e.</hi> th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> never feel the S<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ng of death nor fall under its power, but are enabled by the Faith of the Son of God perfectly to vanquiſh <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> King of Terrors; yea though death aſſail them in his moſt affrighting ſhape, yet is he not able to remove them from their ſtedfaſtneſs, or to abate their Joyes; we have innumerable proofs of this in the End of thoſe Holy Martyrs, who though they have been called to ſeal their Witneſs for God by violent, yea by moſt cruel kinds of death, have notwithſtanding finiſhed their courſe with a moſt Glorious Peace, and rejoycing in the hope of their calling: Howbeit I ſhall not here inſiſt on any of thoſe inſtances; But to let you ſee that death in it's darkeſt dreſs is welcome to a man aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſured
<pb n="221" facs="tcp:204449:117"/> of his Intereſt in Chriſt, and Peace with God, take the ſtory of one <hi>Sebaldus Munſter</hi> a Civilian, that flouriſhed about the year, 1540. Whom it plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed the Lord to viſit with the Plague, of which he dyed at <hi>Wittenberg,</hi> in a time when a general ſickneſs raged there. This perſon, when ſome of his Friends came to viſit and Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fort him a few hours before his death; he ſhewed to them the Swellings and peſtiferous Ulcers which were broken out in his Hand and Arm; ſay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing,</p>
            <p>
               <q>And how do theſe Brace<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lets and precious Gemms wherewith my Chriſt hath adorned me, pleaſe you?</q>
            </p>
            <p>At which words when they brake forth into Tears, he far<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther ſaid,</p>
            <p>
               <q>Let not theſe by any means
<pb n="222" facs="tcp:204449:118"/> ſeem loathſome unto you; for with this Wedding-appa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rel am I going to enjoy that Heavenly Feaſt which I ſhall have with my Chriſt for ever. Thus ſhall I paſs to that everlaſting Council of moſt Excellent and holy Souls; and thus ſhall I be accepta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble to God my Redeemer.</q>
            </p>
            <p>Thus triumphing and full of Joy did he leave the World, having got a clear ſight of a better, that is an Heavenly Countrey. And though to dye of the Plague may ſeem to Sence very diſmal, yet as <hi>Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtin</hi> hath well obſerved; <hi>lib.</hi> 1. <hi>de Civitate Dei: cap.</hi> 11. <hi>Mala mors putanda non eſt, quam bona vita praeceſſerit,</hi> &amp;c: <hi>i. e.</hi> 
               <q>No kind of Death is to be eſteem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed evil, which hath been preceded by a good Life: for nothing makes Death evil,
<pb n="223" facs="tcp:204449:118"/> but that which follows Death: Therefore they that of neceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſity muſt dye once, need not be Thoughtful by what ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cident they may come to dye, but rather whither they muſt go when they dye.</q> 'Tis an excellent ſaying of the Author of the Book of Wiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom: <hi>chap.</hi> 4. 7. <hi>The Righteous man though prevented by Death, ſhall be in reſt.</hi> The moſt ter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rible or ſuddain ſtroke can make no breach upon his happineſs to whom <hi>to live is Chriſt, and to dye is gain.</hi> They are alwaies ſafe that have made their Cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling and Election ſure; and on the contrary, ſuch are alwayes in danger that live without God in the World. I Remem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber upon occaſion of that paſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſage before cited from the Book of <hi>Wiſdom,</hi> Mr. <hi>Forbs</hi> in his <hi>Inſtr. Hiſtor. Theolog.</hi>
               <pb n="224" facs="tcp:204449:119"/> makes mention of a very me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>morable Story of a pious and learned man that dyed ſuddain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly in his Study; and when ſome were ſcandalized at it, raſhly interpreting this Providence as a Teſtimony of Gods diſplea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure againſt him; it ſo fell out by the wiſe and Gracious or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dering of God (for their Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viction and a teſtimony to his ſervant) that he was found ſitting with a Book open before him, and his finger pointed to theſe words, <hi>Juſtus quâcunque morte preoccupatus fuerit, in refrigerio erit.</hi> i. e. <hi>By what Death ſoever the Righteous man is prevented, he ſhall be in reſt.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>§. 17. Theſe things may ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fice as to my preſent deſign; And therefore I will cloſe all, with the Addition of but one Story more, which for the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>markable
<pb n="225" facs="tcp:204449:119"/> circumſtances of it, may be neither unprofitable nor ungrateful to thoſe Readers which have not acceſs to it in the Latin tongue, for whoſe accommodation and ſervice the whole of this little Tract is in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tended. The Story I intend, is related by the excellent Dr. <hi>Rivet,</hi> in an Epiſtle written not long before his Death to his Brother, <hi>De bonâ Senectute: Of a good Old Age:</hi> And it is this:</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Jacobus Faber</hi> a great reſto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rer both of Polite Learning and Religion in <hi>France,</hi> being a moſt Faithful and eminent Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſter of the Goſpel there, did in a time of very hot Perſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cution Flye with others; and for his ſecurity retired to <hi>Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bret</hi> in <hi>Gaſcoign</hi> to the Queen of <hi>Navarre,</hi> a zealous Profeſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſor and Protectreſs of the Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formed
<pb n="226" facs="tcp:204449:120"/> Religion, with whom he was in Great eſteem: On a certain day the Queen did ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vertiſe him, That ſhe purpoſed to come and dine at his Houſe; and in order thereto invited ſome Learned men with whoſe Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ference ſhe was much pleaſed, to accompany her there. While they were at Dinner, <hi>Faber</hi> be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gan to be exceeding ſad, and now and then to break out in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to tears. At which the Queen complained, and deſired him to tell the cauſe of ſuch heavineſs, when ſhe was come to dine and be merry with him: At laſt he anſwered,</p>
            <p>
               <q>And how can I (moſt Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rene Queen) be chearful my ſelf, or make others chearful, who am the moſt wicked man that the Earth bears.</q>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>And what wickedneſs ſo great</hi> (ſaith ſhe) <hi>can you be guilty of,</hi>
               <pb n="227" facs="tcp:204449:120"/> 
               <hi>who from your Youth have been eſteemed to lead ſo holy a Life.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <q>I am (ſaid he) now of the age of an hundred and one years, and am free from the touch of any Woman in all this time; neither do I re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>member ought that burthens my Conſcience, or ſhould make me afraid to leave the World, except one ſin, which I believe too is pardonable.</q>
            </p>
            <p>And when ſhe preſſed him to declare what it was, he could not ſpeak a while for the abun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dance of tears; but at length ſaid:</p>
            <p>
               <q>How can I ſtand before the Tribunal of God, who have purely and ſincerely taught many the Holy Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpel of the Son of God, who following my Doctrine have conſtantly endured a thou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſand torments, and death it
<pb n="228" facs="tcp:204449:121"/> ſelf; when I my ſelf an un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>conſtant Teacher, did flee? and tho' I had lived long enough, and ſhould not have feared Death, but rather co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veted it, yet I withdrew my ſelf, and cowardly tranſgreſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed the Command of my God.</q>
            </p>
            <p>Whereupon the Queen (as ſhe was very eloquent, and full of Divine Sayings) diſcourſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed largely to him, and did by many Examples ſhew, that the ſame thing had happen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed to many Good and Holy men who were now in the Kingdom of God; and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore he ought not in any wiſe to deſpair of the Goodneſs and Mercy of God towards him. And many things to the ſame purpoſe were added by others preſent.</p>
            <p>Upon which he was com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forted,
<pb n="229" facs="tcp:204449:121"/> and became chearful again; but ſaid,</p>
            <p>
               <q>Now therefore nothing re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mains, but that I go from hence to God, as ſoon as I have made my Will; I have that Impreſsion, that I muſt deferre no longer, for I per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive God calls me.</q>
            </p>
            <p>Then fixing his eyes on the Queen; <q>Madam (ſaid he) I appoint you my Heir; and to your Preacher Mr. <hi>Gerard</hi> I bequeath all my Books; my Cloaths, and whatſoever elſe I have, I give to the Poor. Other things I com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mend to God.</q>
            </p>
            <p>At this the Queen ſmiling, asked, <q>
                  <hi>What then ſhall I have</hi> James <hi>out of the Inheritance?</hi> The care (ſaid he) of diſtri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>buting this to the Poor.</q>
            </p>
            <pb n="230" facs="tcp:204449:122"/>
            <p> 
               <hi>It is well,</hi> (ſaid ſhe) <hi>I ſolemn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly profeſs, this Legacy is more acceptable to me, than if the King of</hi> France <hi>my Brother had named me his Heir.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>After this his Countenance was chearfull; and he ſaid; <q>O Queen, I have need of ſome Reſt; Be ye chearful, and in the mean time <hi>Fare<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wel.</hi> 
               </q>So he left them at Table, and laid him down upon a Bed that was near, where as they thought, he lay ſleeping, but was indeed fallen aſleep in the Lord, without the leaſt ſign of any previous di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtemper; for when they went to awake him they found him dead, to their great admira<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion. Such was the end of this Holy man; which as <hi>Ri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vet</hi> obſerves, leaves to us an
<pb n="231" facs="tcp:204449:122"/> Example of the Mercy of God <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>o this his Servant, in awaken<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ng ſuch a Gracious ſence of <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>is former weakneſs in him, and applying his Pardoning Grace in Chriſt to him be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore he was called hence; and alſo a ſerious Warning unto all, to get their Accounts for another World cleared before they come to dye; That be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing well aſſured of the Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vour of God in Chriſt, and of the Soundneſs of their Faith and Repentance, they may ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pect their Change in Peace: Conſcience is a tender thing, and what we count but ſmall while we live, may make a Dying-bed very uneaſie to us; And therefore as we tender our own Peace and Comfort when we come to Dye, it moſt nearly concerns us to
<pb n="232" facs="tcp:204449:123"/> be Serious while we Live, and as the Apoſtle ſaith, <hi>To walk circumſpectly, not as Fools,</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Epheſ. 5. 15, 16.</note> 
               <hi>but as Wiſe; Redeeming the Time, becauſe the Dayes are evil.</hi>
            </p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
         <div type="publishers_advertisement">
            <pb facs="tcp:204449:123"/>
            <head>
               <hi>Books Printed for and Sold by</hi> Benjamin Alſop <hi>at the An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gel and Bible in the</hi> Poul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trey.</head>
            <p>SIxty one Sermons preached upon publick occaſions by Dr. <hi>Adam Littleton: in fol.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Dr. <hi>Mantons</hi> Sermons on the 119 Pſalm. <hi>Fol.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Some Diſcourſes, Sermons and Remains of the Reverend Mr. <hi>Joſ. Glanvile,</hi> late Rector of <hi>Bath,</hi> and Chaplain in ordinary to his Majeſty. <hi>Quar.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Melius Inquirendum; in</hi> Oct: <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>trum Horum,</hi> or the thirty nine Articles of the Church of <hi>England</hi> at large recited, and compared with the Doctrines
<pb n="210" facs="tcp:204449:124"/> of thoſe commonly called <hi>Preſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>byterian</hi> on the one ſide, and the Tenets of the Church of <hi>Rome</hi> on the other: by <hi>Henry Care: Octavo.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The Hiſtory of the Popiſh Sham plots from the Reign of Queen <hi>Elizabeth</hi> to this very time: <hi>Oct.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Mr. <hi>Baxters</hi> defence of the Nonconformiſts Plea for Peace: <hi>Octavo.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The Holy War, By <hi>John Bunyan: Octa.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Divine Meditations, with a daily directory: by Sir <hi>William Waller: Octa.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>A Diſcourſe of the Covenants that God made with men be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore the Law: by <hi>Nehemia Cox: Octa.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The Glory of Free-grace diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>played: by <hi>Stephen Lobb: Oct.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>A diſcourſe of Temptations
<pb n="211" facs="tcp:204449:124"/> to Atheiſtical and Blaſphemous Thoughts, Self Murder, Deſpair, and Preſumption: by Dr. <hi>John Collings: in Octa.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>A Reaſonable Account why ſome Pious Nonconformiſts Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſters Judge it ſinful, for them to perform their Miniſterial Acts by the preſcribed forms of others: with a Supplement and defence: All three being Replyes to Dr. <hi>Faulkner.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The Schollars daily Task, or Grammer illuſtrated: By <hi>N. S.</hi> a lover of Learning: <hi>Octa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vo.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>A Treatiſe of Scandal, toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther with a Conſideration of Chriſtian Liberty and things indifferent: <hi>Octavo.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The Way of good men for wiſe men to Walk in: <hi>Octa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vo.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Divine Love, or the willing<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs
<pb facs="tcp:204449:125"/> of Jeſus Chriſt to ſave ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ners: By <hi>Vav. Powel.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The Security of Engliſhmens Lives: or the Truſt, Power and Duty of the Grand Juries of <hi>England.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Youngs</hi> Engliſh Scholar, being the moſt plain and eaſieſt method to learn Youth (to ſpell, read and write true Engliſh) Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tant, many having by the help of this twelve-peny Book ſaved their Parents the charge of ſome Years Schooling.</p>
            <div type="part">
               <head>Stitcht Books in Quarto.</head>
               <p>The miſchief of Impoſitions, being an Anſwer to Dr. <hi>Stil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lingfleets</hi> Sermon of Seperati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on.</p>
               <p>Two Funeral Sermons: the one at the Interment of a Young man: the other at the burial
<pb facs="tcp:204449:125"/> of a Young Gentlewoman: Both Preached by <hi>John Shower.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>An Argument for Tollera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion; by a Countrey Gentle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man.</p>
               <p>The Hiſtory of the <hi>Pariſian</hi> Maſſacre.</p>
            </div>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
